He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and
he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st Inok, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is now...
Nevertheless, haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
post this live Colin show.
Focus on-
Enchantment in creation, the union of the scene and unseen as made by God and
experienced by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, wrestlers with the devil. You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast and my co-host,
the very reverend, almost double doctor,
Pentupel master,
Stephen Dion.
Pentupel, Pent-
sex stupor, sex stupor
right? Who knows? Yeah, well, yeah, technically. Yeah, six, six
stupe master.
Father Stephen D. Young is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana,
where it's only in the low 80s, which is weird. And I'm
at a rainy cool day. Yeah. I'm father and just even
Damien can amaze Pennsylvania where it is actually in the 90s.
We're not live today. Oh, like last time, you know what I
I'm not dead.
Yeah, the show is it live. We could be dead by the time of the airs who knows?
Yeah, that could be that's true. Yeah, yeah, which would be very weird and sad
They'd have to play a little bumper at the beginning
Dear listeners this would be our haunting final masterpiece. I know
Like last time this is a pre-recorded episode because unlike last time when it was father Stephen
I'm traveling when this one airs
So people talk about the devil you're traveling to a place where it is it literally impossible to buy a vowel because they don't have it
They don't need...
them. What do you need them for in in Wales? Yeah, yeah, yeah. So people do talk about the
devil, even in Wales, usually in the singular, yet the scripture gives us a number of different
names and descriptions of spirits that might all or some qualify for this role. And if you
figure in second-tiple Jewish literature, the list gets even longer. So with this episode,
we're going to look at the list, try to make some sense of it. So we're going to go
and take a break from...
our series on the apocrypha or are we? Yes we are. Oh good. I mean we are going to talk about
there'll be some reference that are second double Jewish literature but we always do that. So
that's true. If we don't consider this a break that means our whole show has been one long series on
that's probably true. There's probably not an episode we haven't made some reference to it.
Yeah. Yeah. At some point. Get get father Steven's apocrypha book everybody. It's the footnote
Did you ever have-
I have to listen again. Oh wait no, that's right.
That's right.
You say all kinds of time.
Right, so yeah.
So the devil.
There's definitely that phrase used in the Bible, right?
The devil.
He's in the details.
Yes. Yes.
I'm giving it to understand.
Yes.
I don't know if that's referring to the magazine or.
I do not hate that magazine.
Yeah.
Good.
It was sort of great value maximum which was
That's a phrase I've never heard before yes like
Anyway, so the those dide these quote-unquote man's magazines are best
It's sort of like new metal. We should just like bury it
Like memory hole it never think of it or speak of it again. Yeah
Although it does occur to me that I have not yet played the Lord of Spirits
I have not played the Lord of Spirits.
metal theme in a long time. It's not new metal. It's like with the NU. It's no, I don't know, kind of more 80s
late 80s metal. You'd have to put it like some record scratches and like
repetitive lyrics.
Yes. This is how you remind me. Okay.
No, they're not new. I know. I know, but that's I was just reminded of that.
You know, you don't have to say everything that comes into your head, Father Andrew, just because I do. Yeah, I was gonna say
Hey, when you started that, I was like, what?
Well, you do. Exactly.
If I jumped off a cliff would you anyway?
Hens on which cliff?
Which hill I choose to die on.
Some would say you are a hill that one would choose to die on, but that's possible.
Tough but fair.
So, this episode...
We're being transparent here, right?
And there are going to be some other episodes like this in the future.
Right?
So some of the stuff, especially early on in the show, you recognize this.
Oh, hey, this is stuff they kind of talked about a long time ago, way back in the long ago
time.
In the Mexican radio period?
Yes, the early days.
And you will be correct.
Now we're not going to say the exact same things because...
You know, I can't even remember most of what I said yesterday, let alone what I said, you know, three years ago.
But we're also going to be coming at it from a different angle, right? We're taking a different approach to it.
But for a few reasons, right?
One of them being again, that there is a new angle, there is going to be a lot new tonight and how we approach this and how we talk about it.
but also because a lot of those early episodes for those who...
who've actually listened to them,
were interrupted by things like power outages.
Right now.
That could still happen.
My voice turned into a robot and Mexican radio
and all kinds of other things.
And especially in the very early episodes,
we were still theoretically trying to do a one hour show.
Right.
With about the same amount of material
that we used now in our three, three and a half hour shows.
So things that ended up getting condensed and left out, all kinds of things happen.
All kinds of things happen.
So now that we've experienced large S, we can return to some of these topics,
go through them more thoroughly, come out them from other angles, flesh things out some more.
So that's what we're doing today on this topic.
If you're sitting there thinking, well, you talked about that before, kind of,
a lot of different episodes.
And we'll do that sometimes in the future, especially with some of that.
Some of the stuff we talked about really early on.
We've actually already done that a couple of times.
Sure.
But like for example, we did very early on, we did the five-ish falls of the angels like
classic episode now I guess because it's old.
And then we did a set of three episodes on the three sort of
of humanity later, where we were talking about some of the same things, but from a different
angle, a different perspective, and fleshing them out more. Obviously, three episodes compared to one
episode. It got fleshed out a lot more. So, we've already been doing that. We're doing that tonight.
There'll still be somebody in the comments like, I heard some of this before, right, in the comments.
I have found that I have, though, I am not a prophet nor a son of a prophet, the ability to predict a
a lot of you.
two comments like before the fact.
For the last one, it's almost like you willed them into being.
Yes, I just had to put that.
I gave a script and people showed up and willingly followed it for some reason.
And ironically.
God bless you guys.
That's...
But yeah, so we're going to be talking about devil figures.
Right? Big bads. Final bosses.
Right, the, the uh...
the sort of ultimate evil,
dude slash spirit slash thing slash, right?
And as I said in other episodes,
we've talked about any given episode,
maybe one or two of these and come at it
from different perspectives, different trajectories through it.
But as we've mentioned,
at various times and as we're going to talk about in the third half just to, you know, tease
what we're doing at the end. No one, there is no place in Second Temple Jewish literature,
or the Church Fathers, or the Scriptures themselves, where anybody said, like lists,
all of the figures that we're going to talk about tonight.
as like separate figures.
Right. That doesn't happen.
What you get is different texts, even different
texts within the canonical scriptures, but then also different second-template Jewish texts,
different patricity texts, different other things. We'll talk about sort of this figure of
ultimate evil.
maybe two of them, right, sometimes, and describe that figure in certain terms, according
to a certain pattern, right?
And as you look at multiple texts, you see these patterns emerge.
And sometimes those patterns of description are attached to particular names for this
figure.
Sometimes they aren't necessarily.
Yeah, sometimes they're attached to titles, basically.
Yeah, or sometimes this description will have several of the names that we're going to talk about on this episode all thrown onto the one figure.
Just sort of balling them all up into this one figure.
Right. And using multiple patterns.
Let's say when we talk about a figure, we're not just talking about her name.
Although obviously different names.
used for that figure are going to be a key differentiator.
Yeah.
And we're also not just talking about a certain description
because there are names and other factors in places
where these scriptures blend together.
But we're trying to, each one of these figures
we're describing is going to be describing one
of those patterns itself.
And eventually, we're going to talk
about how mutually exclusive they are.
or aren't and what's going on with all this.
But so when this is premiering on YouTube,
there's gonna be folks,
I'm making another prediction,
I'm pulling another Crescan.
Who early on are gonna say in the live chat,
they're gonna say,
well wait, how does this one relate to this other one?
Is it just hold on?
We'll get there.
Don't worry.
show is not brief. Yes, we have to we have to we have to set the stage a little bit. Right? First, we have to sort of lay out who the players are.
You can't tell the players without the program. So we're giving you the programs you can tell the players and then we'll talk about the relationships of that kind of thing. Yeah. And there's an important important meta issue, right as we're kind of sitting the stage, which is.
is like some people might say, well, okay, do these just do these different...
sources disagree with each other or, you know, like, because the point of these traditions,
as they're described in these various text, various writers, as you mentioned outside of scripture,
is not that they're all trying, they're like some tracking down some elusive
Tasmanian devil, you know, they're not searching for some species and attempting to describe it and,
and you know, taxonomy.
or whatever.
Rather, when you're trying to analyze this kind of thing,
you have to look at it as a set of traditions
and then see what they have in common,
see what it is that is the point of the traditions?
Like, why were they written down?
What was this aimed at?
And, you know, this connects with a lot of the discussions
we've had about how to read the Bible
and stuff like that.
If you look at it as an attempt that to make sort of
a kind of science of demonology, then...
you're going to miss what this is all about.
I mean, you can get the,
what is it called, the dictionary of deities
and demons in the Bible,
which is a really interesting and fascinating book.
But that's not the point of all this stuff.
And in fact, the book doesn't even take that point of view
like it's an attack.
Right. It's descriptive, not a pre-script.
Yeah, it just says this is what we see.
And that's what we're going to try to do with this episode.
We're going to say, look, these are the things
that we see in these texts.
What do these texts seem?
to be doing. You know, so that's, that's, you know, if you want to get the really cool
stuff of the scientific demonologies side though, you got to, you got to dig into some late
medieval and early modern manuscripts. Oh, sure. I mean, they get obsessed with that.
They've got pictures. They've got like drawing. I know. I know.
Of different demons. Right. And I think, I mean, right, like, like, you know, this is what
kind of cool, but it's fanfic. Yeah, exactly. I mean, this is what forms the basis of, like,
a number of different volumes of D&D books, right?
It's interesting and fun.
right, but we shouldn't try to kind of materialize that which is inherently immaterial.
Yeah.
You know?
It's like the official head book of the Marvel Universe.
A hot mood.
I used to sit there and read those.
You can't quantify the Hulk's strength.
Right.
The matter he gets the stronger he gets.
He gets it here and put tonnage on that.
I know.
What are you thinking?
Thank you.
Yeah. Apologies to the editor of the official handbook of the Marvel Universe, the late
great Mark Grumwald. But anyway, I used to have those in a series of paperbacks that combined
multiple of the comic volumes into one. And I would sit down and read them for hours. I
loved those. See, that's like extra nerdy. Like, you weren't even reading like the comic
stories about the character. I did that too but you know.
You were just reading theoretically about the character.
Basically in psychopedias, I've always loved reading
at psychopedias.
I know.
It's a little lame.
OK.
Yeah.
It's a metal level that you reached there.
You know, they have, they have.
This is not a commercial.
I'm not recommending anything.
But they have, they have combined all of those old things,
both the official handbook of the World of the Universe.
And...
Who's who in the DCU which was the DC Comics version?
Yeah.
Into these giant omnibus hard covers.
Wow.
They're like 1,400 pages.
Yeah.
So now it even looks like it, it's like LaPedia.
I know.
I had the deluxe edition.
That's why I was the O'Hote mood and not O'Hote mood.
You got to get the deluxe edition.
Deluxe edition, yeah.
Yeah.
Because the original head book was two spars.
I think I like this.
I mean, now there were 17 minutes into the episode.
I think that I liked it a lot because, I mean, it's related, right?
This is sort of, you know, taxonomically related to what we're discussing.
There was a lot of really good art in there.
Yeah, there was some good art.
And I learned about a whole lot of characters from comic books that I had never read, you
know, because I just sit there and thumb through it and read like every entry, you know.
So well, you could find obscure goofy characters in there too.
Yeah.
Oh, yeah.
Like...
Okay, I understand why someone had was under a deadline
and thought this was a good idea for one issue,
but why are we preserving its memory here?
See, this is related to the second time
we'll do a slitter, too.
All right.
I don't think they had deadlines.
No, no deadlines.
Time works differently in the before times.
So yeah, let's talk about the devil.
The devil.
Who is in the details as we already covered.
Exactly, exactly.
So heads, it's cyclopedias, segue.
Okay.
So yeah, so we'll start with the devil, right?
Deal bolos.
Yes, the devilos in Greek.
LD oblum.
Which means the one who throws apart, see I should play the etymology theme for that.
Okay, butterfly.
Yes, he's the opposite of symbol, you know, the one with the throwing together.
The throwing apart.
Yeah.
Actually, it means the slander.
But oh, man.
That's.
You're better.
You're capable of such a better etymology than that.
I know.
I've got a good one.
I've got I'm saving for later.
Go ahead.
T's it.
Yeah.
This is what
happens when we pre-record by the way we get even more rambo
because you don't have anyone watching us.
I think we say that every time now.
Yeah.
What we do is a disclaimer.
That's right.
What?
Like literally the person who normally keeps an eye on us,
like left the studio.
You are unattended.
No one's watching.
So yes.
We're just getting up to nonsense.
So the devil.
So there's an underlying, we've talked about this before on the show way back in the long
ago time.
There is a basic pagan narrative, there's some good books about this that we've recommended
before that goes throughout ancient Near Eastern paganism, including ancient Greek religion.
in.
that is called by scholars now the succession myth,
which boiled down is the idea that whoever the most high God
is now, whichever of the gods is seen as the king
of the gods or the most high God
or the supreme-raining God now
was not the original most high God.
Yeah, he's a usurper.
There's been another...
others plural beforehand, and yes, and that the way he took power was not that the old one
died of old age and left the throne to him, but that he staged some kind of revolution or coup
or violent action. And usually it is the action of a son against his father.
Yeah, so the probably best known version of this to our listeners would be in Greek mythology
where Zeus is considered to be the most high God,
but he got it by taking out his father,
Kronos, who got it by taking out his father,
Uranous or Uranus, however you want to pronounce it.
And it was not a, an abdication as it were.
Yes, no, no.
The second case, it was a castration.
So yeah, there's two layers in mythology.
We've talked before on the show.
And the reason there's two layers of Greek mythology.
is that when we're talking about Greek mythology,
we're really talking about Hessey in here.
So we're talking about Greek religion
as Hesseyid sort of lays it out, right?
And Hesseyid is synthesizing.
Yeah.
Right.
As we've talked about before,
Greek city states had their own God or couple of gods,
like Athens, it was Athena, obviously,
and less obviously Hephaestus.
He's in the basement somewhere.
He's making stuff.
So, you know, when he synthesizes the relationships between all of these gods, we tend to have this sort of justice league view of ancient religion, where they had these pantheons and they worship the pantheons, and that's not accurate, right?
right the pantheons are later constructs.
Yeah.
Of taking all of these local gods.
Once there is a greater sense, right?
So there's a sense now.
It's not just Athens.
or Sparta or Corinth or whichever city state you want to name, it's the Greeks, right?
Where there's this larger identity or a larger identity is sort of being forged that you start
to get the idea that oh well the gods of that city state and this 80 state are related to each other.
Right and there are these connections and if there's been strife between those city states
to the pan.
that gets mirrored, right? It's strife between their gods and all that. So Hesse it is synthesizing at that level, but Hesse it is also
in a way parallel to like I just mentioned strife between cities becoming strife between the deities. He's also dealing with
the history of the people group. And so the reason there's two layers ultimately at Hesse it is that Hesse that first layer
with basically having
and Earth, right? The Sky God and the Earth Goddess is in the sort of the Indo-European religion.
Underlying the people group, right? And then the transition from that to something Greek,
inherited from the Near East and then the second transition is the typical ancient Near Eastern
transition. Right.
And to give another example of the specific Near Eastern transition, probably the most relevant one immediately to the Old Testament,
and we're going to talk about this more in a minute, is Bale and his father, L.
And it's not coincidental that Bale's a storm god.
This is part of this pattern.
So this idea of this sort of
of revolution in the heavenly places between where a divine son sort of ceases the throne
from his father.
Now you may point out, Bale actually seized it from Yom.
This is true, but read about how Bale and his sister wife treat their father.
You'll notice some things.
But this is just how...
this is in every religion in the ancient areas, that this sort of succession happened.
And so the Hebrew Scriptures present us with a story that is sort of a counter story to
this. And the story presented by the Hebrew Scriptures is that there was an attempted
revolution, as it were, right? An attempted accession, an attempted sort of overthrow or
an attempted rebellion, but the rebel didn't win.
Yeah, and I mean, this is one of the things that underlines how different the most high
God of Israel is versus the most high God of other religious groups, which is that his
is eternal, absolute and invincible, whereas in every pagan religion, that is just not true.
You know, the gods can be taken out by other gods or hurt or you know, usurped or whatever.
Right. They're just as weaker according to the actual stories themselves, the pagan gods are weaker.
Yes, yes.
And this is what's going on in Isaiah.
right? Isaiah and Isaiah God says, you know, before me there was none and after me there will be no other, right?
And our Plato brain instantly kicks in and we're like, oh he's saying he's eternal.
Right? It's true that God is eternal, right? But that's not what he's saying in Isaiah.
Yeah, no, he's saying because I've always been in charge. No one else will ever be in charge except for me.
Yes, yes, there's not some other but wasn't supposed I got to the past to heal over through.
and there's no one gonna come along and overthrow him because we're the context of the Assyrians.
Right, the Babylon, who all had these stories, right, that were deeply embedded into their religion.
And again, I used the mythology word which I probably shouldn't have, right, because that may have
led people down a familiar trail to thinking of these, oh, these are the stories they're telling.
These are just stories they're telling to explain something rather but of course
That's not how ancient religion worked, right?
These stories are abstracted from the actual,
religious ritual life of these peoples.
Right, so in Babylon, the accession of Marduk
to the throne was this massively huge festival,
like the key main primary religious festival of the year.
Right, the enthromative bale at Ugarit
was V-BIG.
religious vessel of the year, a route which their whole religious system was structured.
In a sense, almost the pagan versions of the ascension.
Right.
Yeah.
And so, it's not just a story.
That would be like saying, well, there's this Christian story that Jesus rose from the
dead.
Yeah.
Right.
I mean, someone could say that, but it would show they don't know much about Christianity.
Right or how Christianity works as a religion right
We tend to think that way again because
The religions we're talking about like Babylonian Russia is dead
And so for us now it is just mythology. It's just all that's left is this story
Yeah, and the actual embodiment of it the living out of it and all of this
that went on.
in the past, you know, 25 centuries ago is gone, right, and not there anymore for us to really
understand. So this is a key story, and so whether Hebrew scriptures counter this story,
they're fundamentally undermining the basis of the religious life of Israel's neighbors.
Alright, there is...
There is no panheracy of ecumenism in the Hebrew Scriptures.
Right, there is no...
Well, you could call him L, you could call him Yahweh, you could call him Warta, you know,
it's all good.
There is no that is not a thing.
It's not remotely a thing in the Hebrew Scriptures.
were certainly according to the Hebrew Scriptures is
realite to try to go down that.
road. Yeah, right, but in a there in the Hebrew Scriptures, right? That's what's
being condemned by the Hebrew Scriptures. So the place where we actually get the
counter story, and we mentioned this, I don't know if it was last episode or the
episode before that, times of flat circle and all blurs together, we're always
talking about this.
But the place where that is the scriptures even though it's maybe not immediately apparent to us because of how we're used to reading it is Genesis chapter 3
And that's been so firmly
Worked into us as this is a story where something bad happens to humanity
humanity. Which is true, right? But it's true. Not all that's going to happen.
But that's not it, right? Yes, that's not it. Yeah, if you look at if you look at icons of the
expulsion from paradise, you can see the angel with the flaming sword. You can see Adam and Eve
leaving. But if you look down at their feet, this is pretty much I haven't seen an orthodox icon
where this wasn't the case. Maybe there are some. I don't know. I'm not going to say that none are
like this. But usually you look down at their feet, you can see the serpent being driven out from the
the garden as well.
And the serpent, of course, we said this a bunch of times on the show is not a snake, right?
This is not how the snake lost its legs.
Snakes don't talk.
Well, maybe animals did talk, remember Julie's.
Right. But yeah, this is not a talking snake. This is not. Right.
We've talked before on the show.
how the word Nikash that's used to describe him, the cool thing with Hebrew words is that
you only write the consonants and there's three consonants in all the words, right? And
depending on how you vocalize it, meaning depending on what vowels you effectively add
when you pronounce it, it can be different parts of speech, right? So the word Nikash can
mean depending on whether it's an adjective and adverb and noun, a part of simple, right?
can mean different things.
And so, and the writers of the Hebrew Scriptures deliberately use that aspect of Hebrew as a feature, not a book.
So if you study Hebrew especially if you're a Latin-minded kind of person like St. Jerome was, you find this endlessly frustrating because Hebrew is not a precise language.
Yeah.
It's got two verb tenses neither
which have anything to do with time.
Right, I don't like it.
There just isn't precision in the Hebrew language.
But again, the writers use that as a feature.
They don't see it as a bug.
And so they use it especially in Hebrew poetry,
but even elsewhere to convey multiple ideas
with the same word.
Right, that ambiguity you could read it this way,
or you could read it that way to him.
and they apply both meanings, right?
And there are places where new Testament authors
try to do that in Greek.
That's a lot harder to do in Greek
because we get to say more precisely.
Yeah, I just say it's, it is much more precise.
Yeah, not as precise as Latin,
but it is more precise.
But one big example is in the state of John's Gospel,
in the state of Johns gospel, Christ is speaking to St. Nicodemus.
and says to him, you must be born in Greek anothen, which can mean again, or it can mean from above, which does say John mean.
Yes. Exactly. Are you back and forth Mrs. The Point? Right? He means both. Right? Like it's deliberately.
It's deliberately implying both ideas.
Right?
So you could do that.
And so that, I think, is what would argue, and a lot of other scholars would argue, is
what's going on with Nikash in Genesis 3 is that you're getting the idea, yes, serpent,
from the noun.
But also it can mean the shining one and it can mean the
subtle or deceptive or winding one.
Right, which of those does it mean?
Yes.
Right.
It means it means all three of those.
And when you take into account that
Sarah Femme as we've talked about on the show before,
were presented as serpentine
and jealous beings, right?
Then this idea all makes sense.
Shining one makes sense for an angelic being
Serpent makes it
if we're talking about something like a seraphim and subtle crafty, right? Obviously, that's
what he is, right? Deceptive or treacherous. So this is describing a spiritual being,
right? An angelic being. And when the curse is given in Genesis 3,
Again, we tend to focus on the curse on humanity.
But...
The serpent gets cursed too.
Yeah.
And the serpent,
when the serpent is cursed,
we mentioned this recently, I know.
He's told, you know, he's going to crawl on his belly
and eat the dust of the earth.
As we mentioned then, and other times before,
ancient people weren't dumb.
They'd use snakes to eat dirt.
They'd seen them eat rodents.
Right? That's...
That's it.
And so the dust there is the same word of r that's used for dust you from dust you were
right from dust you were made and to dust you will return.
Yeah, so the idea is that he's eating death.
Yeah, the death.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Yeah, once we get the images of the hell mouth, this gigantic serpentine mouth swallowing
up dead humanity.
Right. And so, and he's cast down...
to erets, which is the word for earth or the land or the ground in Hebrew, but is also
used to refer to the underworld.
So he wants to bow up on high.
He's this heavenly being.
He gets cast down into the underworld.
He wants power and authority.
He's given death.
And this is what Hebrew's 214 is referring to when it refers to the devil as the
who has the power of death. Now in terms of what constitutes his rebellion, I know I've
slammed Milton enough, but pre-Milton will just say again, as we have before, pre-Milton,
there's not really anybody. There's definitely nobody among the church fathers and nobody
and second temple Judaism that thinks there
was a rebellion of Lucifer and his angels in primordial time before the world was created.
Where they all got thrown out of heaven.
Nobody says that.
I say definitely not the church of others.
I add that other stuff because there's probably somebody out there.
I'm not a scholar of the medieval period.
So Milton may have been drawing on something from the late medieval period.
or something that I just don't know about.
And it may predate Milton by 100 years or something, maybe.
I don't know.
But Milton's the first major, and Milton's where we all get it.
Right, there was a paradise lost, that reading of who
the devil is.
That's not anywhere.
Everybody else, everybody before that,
talks about the devil.
And sometimes these, this figure is identified with some of the other figures we're going to talk about, but the devil has fallen after the creation of the world.
To quote St Andrew of Cessaria in his commentary on the book of Revelation, which we're going to come back to a little later.
All the fathers say, he says, we must accept what all the fathers say, after the creation
of the world, the devil fell through envy.
Right. So, now in terms of when exactly the angels were created?
Yes, there's a variety of thoughts about that.
Right. But it's always within the creation of the, within the creation story of Genesis.
Yeah. Yeah.
So some fathers and Jewish writers you'll see the first day, the first day and the fourth day are the most popular.
Fourth day because of the connection between
the stars than angels. There are some outliers though. There are some second-day people.
There are some, right, some other. The second-day people, it's because that's the waters above
from the waters below. So that's like the heavens from the deep from the abyss. So they're connected
to the abyss to the the volumineals. So there's different, right, and there are fathers who say,
I felt pretty much instantly.
Right. But the envy that we're talking about is envy of humanity. Right. Which means there must
in some sense be humanity. Right. And so yeah, so again, the Milton thing, we have it our head that,
that the devil wanted to get rid of God as God and make himself God.
sees the throne. Which is obviously drawing on these succession myth ideas. Succession myths,
right? Yes. But here's the thing. In the succession myths, part of the underlying presupposition is
that each of the gods is in some sense finite and equivalent to one another. Whereas that's not
the perspective of the Scriptures. So as I've posed to people
before when talking about this, right?
You're a creature just like the devil is.
You want to make God not be God anymore
and you want to make yourself God
so that you have all of God's power ability,
however you want to talk about it, right?
There's problems even figuring out how to talk about it.
But what's step one, right?
Look, that's not a thing you can do.
Yeah.
and the devil
You know, may in some ways be have a different set of powers and potentialities than you do.
Right. And you might consider those powers to be greater.
But that's not possible for him either.
There's not a way to do that.
Right. There's just not a way to do that.
So that dog don't hunt. Right.
Um, so this envy thing again, this is all tied to humanity.
Right, and the idea of envy comes from again a close read of the Hebrew Scriptures, right?
What is man that you are mindful of him? You made him a little lower than the angels, but you crowned him with glory and honor.
Right, so humanity has these unique qualities invested in humanity by God that are going to ultimately lead
ultimately we know in the Messiah in Christ
to them being exalted far above the angels.
Humanity has, while they may not have the same powers that the adjelic beings have invested
in them, at least at the time of their coming into being, they have potentialities that
angels don't possess.
One very important one coming to share in the divine nature, right?
Theosis.
It comes about through salvation, right?
That's where the envy comes in.
Yeah, because you man...
humanity is destined for literally greater things in the angels.
Yes, and this even in some text,
it's a second-devil Jewish text, is literalized in the idea that humanity is
made in the image of God.
So the devil and the other angels are commanded when Adam is created to
worship and serve him as the image of God.
And the devil and some like him say nope.
Refuse. Right. Now there's some there's some problematic elements of that. But I think that tradition is referred to in Hebrews for example amongst other places.
A variation of it at least.
So, but that's the idea here. The idea here is that out of that envy, right? The devil can't.
do anything to God. Right? There's not only to harm God, right? But he can go after God's creation.
He can go after other created beings. They're created like him. He can try to destroy them,
corrupt and destroy them, and especially the creation that he's most envious of.
right, which God loves and fights so precious humanity.
the devil can set out to destroy humanity.
And so that's what this rebellion is about.
Right, and that's how he rebels.
He shows up and he talks to the woman in the garden.
And sort of seduces her toward evil by promising her,
ironically by promising her a kind of theosis by another means.
Yeah, it's sort of like, I've got a shortcut.
Yeah.
And so that's why he is cursed also.
Right? That's why he suffers this downfall also.
And so this is a reversal.
Right? This is where St. Paul gets all the gods of the nations or demons.
Right? These things, your worshiping. Right?
You bail worshippers are basically devil worshippers.
You martyck worshippers are basically devil worshippers.
You
You're worshiping this being who's feeding you this line, giving you this propaganda about no really I won.
Yeah.
You should worship me, right, rather than the creator, the one who defeated him, the one who threw him down into the underworld.
And if you continue doing that, you're going to end up following that same trajectory into the underworld with him.
Yeah, you become like what's your worship.
Yeah, and that's what you get the Hebrew Scriptures and if you want
particular places where this argument is made, sort of narratively, going back to Isaiah,
Isaiah 14 verses 3 through 21.
Right? This is where the name Lucifer comes out of the Latin translation.
Right? What it actually says in the Hebrew is, hello Ben-Shakar.
And that seems to be there.
I've been to a couple of really good journal articles making this...
argument. Not just in general, not just what is that hell in hell, Ben Chicare.
That's right.
Chicare was the name of the Morningstar. That gets translated to Latin as Lucifer
some of the morning. Yeah, well, and also that's the name of the the
Don God in in Ugritic religion. Right. Yeah. These the mornings.
That's the more it's the shakar is literally the name for the morning star. Yeah, yeah, right and so then
From that that star is associated with the god
It's the morning star the morning, right? So Ben Ben means son of right in Hebrew son of the morning
That's how he gets yeah son of the morning and some translations
Right and so first of all there's well. What is this hell? Oh this name?
right? What is that supposed to be? So there's an argument for that.
that also going through the details of the story, the way he's described, right, and sort
of his fall is described into the underworld and this kind of thing. They're very good
argument, scholarly arguments down, very journal articles, and this is actually talking about
Enlil, hmm, who was in Mesopotamian specifically Babylon in the region around it, religion was
the most high God who was displaced.
by Marduk.
Right. Now you may be thinking I thought Marduk killed his mother team.
You'd be right. Right. That's the ritual story.
When I say N-Lil was displaced by Marduk, I mean as a political reality,
as we move from the Babylonian period, which then collapses and then the beginning of the Neo-Babalonian period.
Good.
Right? Marduk becomes the most high god politically because of the city, because of religious power dynamics. Right?
This becomes the god who becomes most worship as opposed to Enlil who had previously been
the god who was the center of worship. And so that political and historical reality in Mesopotamian religion
gets reflected in new stories and ritualized.
as the fall of Enlil.
Hmm.
Right, so this is sort of a late religious development.
And there are a whole bunch of parallels
between, you could go research this more if you're super into it,
between the, like the details of the way Isaiah describes this
and those fall of Enlil stories,
where he's replaced by Marta.
to get going down and...
underworld and all of that, all that stuff. So here Isaiah, right, based on who he's talking to,
right, takes one of their stories and sort of inverts it, it makes it about the devil, right,
to make the point that you guys are worshiping the loser.
not the winner.
Right?
Because they're counter the Pro-Devil propaganda.
And then there's another example of this in Ezekiel, chapter 28, verses 11 through 19.
This one may be a little more well-known, at least in some circles.
This is usually grouped together in most English Bibles, one through 19 as this oracle against
the King of Tire.
assuming it's talking about the human king, right? And then most commentaries and stuff
you read will say something like, at some point of this, it seems to shift to talking about
the devil. Yeah, it's a human king. It's weird to read it with that way because, like,
it, I mean, if you read the text, people, you'll see that it says, you know, you were a guardian
and you were walking on the
Mountain of God, you know, stones of fire, like all this stuff, it's like, okay,
that's not describing any kind of earthly
Palace or whatever, you know, right
And if you track really closely with it in verses one through ten, it's talking to the Prince of Tyre
And those are the verses where it seems to be talking about the human king and
Then in 11 to 19, it switches to the king of Tyre
Now I don't know how accurately that's reflected in some English translations.
But in the Hebrew there's a distinction there.
So the text is talking about the human king and calling him the prince.
And then it talks about the king, the guy who's really in charge, using these terms, talking
about the guardian chair of forbidden who's cast down in this.
And so the primary god of tire in Phoenicia is ban...
And so this again is an inversion of the story of Bale's Ascent and Enthronement.
Right? No, actually he lost. Actually he got thrown down.
And just to cover it here, because we're going to go through a bunch of different names for, you know, the big evil guy,
evil guy, one we're not going to go through is be else above because be
is a form of the name Bale. Yeah, same same guy. Right. Bale's above is a corruption
by Enhebrew, like a deliberate one. Right. That's a deliberate one. That's Chris, I one of the titles
of Bale. So one of the titles given to Bale by Bale worshipers was Baal Zabool, which means something
like
High Lord Bale. It's almost literally Lord of lords, right? But it's sort of, you know,
the great Lord Bale, right? Because Bale, the name means Lord. And whereas Bale's above
famously means, right, Lord of the Flies. Yeah. And I think people don't fully appreciate
that. It's not talking about kids. No, no, it's crazy. You're the Lord of the Dung heap,
video.
Yes, where do flies congregate?
Yeah.
Right.
The fly congregation, right?
At best, you've got corpses.
But more realistically, since we're in an agricultural economy, we're talking about
Dung.
Right?
And not snowcow.
Dung either.
No.
So they are talking Dung on bail, what they call him, a beehive about.
That's...
to, uh, right on it, right? But so this is, it's pretty clear here, right? So we have this
devil figure, this sort of attempted rebellion out of envy against the creator, gets thrown
down into the underworld. And this idea of the devil most folks are familiar with. We're
starting here in our first half with the devil you know.
Who I guess is better than those we're gonna talk about it the second half who are the devil?
Devils you don't know that's what people say
Maybe not know maybe not know as well
So of course the other very common we know
Name for the devil is Satan
Right and often people will just sort of treat these as two different names for the same
being
Which they could be which they could be but not necessarily as well
Right.
Yeah.
There's also a separate set of traditions around a figure called various forms of the
name Satan.
And these may be two separate sets of traditions about the same being.
They could be two different sets of traditions, two different beings.
Again, we're going to get into that more toward the end of the show, this episode, which
could be the end of the show.
But it could probably.
You can all get
melted by the weather down there.
Yeah.
So this fella, Satan, right?
The first time we see him in the Hebrew Scriptures
is in the book of Job.
Yeah, where there's, it says the sons of God
all line up in front of God.
And then one comes and starts talking to God about Job.
Yeah.
And I say sort...
because again we use Satan like it's a name.
Like there's a dude named Satan.
And there are traditions, even Jewish traditions in which his name is Satan.
But in Job he's Hossatant, he's V Satan.
And Satan or Satan means adversary or enemy.
So it's the V enemy, V adversary.
but in Hebrew
So if you know a little bit about biblical languages, you might know that in Greek sometimes you have an article
Greek doesn't really have a definite article and has an article
But in Greek sometimes you use the article before names. We don't do that in English. Yeah
unless you're bad. I remember when I was first reading learning Greek and
the textbook that we used there is this
farmer character named D. K. Opelus and
And you know most of the senses started out with O-V-K-O-Polis.
or like wait, the decapulist, that's his, what?
But you know, but that's really common.
Like, you know, for my name, O Andres, the Andrew,
that's right, because the language
hasn't worked the same way as English.
Right, the reason for that, for the record is that
it's actually the article in Greek, at this point,
is still really the demonstrative pronoun.
Yeah, that decapulist, that, meaning the same one.
Yes.
So it is...
continuous narrative, right? You'll use the article after you first
introduced the person, you use the article to indicate you're talking
about the same guy. Right. Because as you notice pretty quickly
reading through like the gospels, for example, you'll have a bunch
of people with the same first name. Yeah. Right. So many
judes, Judas is yeah. And so you might have three Mary's in a
room right and so that form of
Make sense to say hey, we're talking about the same one
Right and then something and that's why you'll get these constructions when they're translated in English like the other Mary
Right right or the other junior Judas not is scary
You know, it's not that like it's almost sounds like I put down in English, right? We say the other Mary
Yeah, like oh, yeah that one. Yeah, right, but that's not what it means. It's just differentiating it what from
the one they were just talking about. Right. Right. This one, that one. Right.
Like, these are two different people. Um, but yes, you do that in Greek. You don't do that in Hebrew.
You don't put the definite article before a name. Uh, Hebrew has other ways of doing continuous
narrative. So you know, you're talking about the same person. Um,
So when we have the definite article here every time Satan
is used, at least in Job it's not being used as a name. It's a title it's referring to
a figure who's fulfilling a certain role. And we see him fulfilling that role in Job.
Right, where he comes and he's sort of making accusations against Job. Right, he says to
God, you know, oh yeah, he's faithful and he loves you and everything, but that's because
you know, you've made him rich and you've given him all these blessings, right? Anyone
wood if you gave them all this right.
you know, start taking some of that stuff away from him and then maybe he won't, you know,
love you so much or be so faithful, right? So he's making accusations, right? He's he's he's a
spiritual being because he's there with the sons of God, with the angelic beings, but he has this
particular role, right? As as an accuser or an adversary, the devil's advocate as it were.
And so surrounding this figure,
there are sort of related figures that you find in second-tabled Jewish literature.
One of them is really on the nose and that's an angel or an archangel that's referred to as
satanael. Yeah.
It's a state, right? So Satan's in the name, right? The Saint of God. The adversary. Yeah.
Yeah, the adversary.
of God. But also there's a figure called Somal, usually transliterated English, S-A-A-M-A-E-L.
And that means the poison of God. Yes, it means the poison of God. I don't recommend googling
Samal. Just for the record, you get a lot of weird, like, Nephilim, Slashvik and stuff. You
You don't even want to go there.
Yeah.
Right, and like goofy.
Not like the spooky scary kind of occult stuff,
like the cringey domicolt stuff.
Right.
So yeah, so just put that out there, fair warning.
You know, if you go look, that's on you.
But in terms of second-templature, right?
And Jewish thought at that point.
That poison of God is that he's the archangel.
What?
of the seven archangels. So we've talked about before, like the archangel Gabriel, the archangel Michael
Uriel Raphael, right? Who are the four you get in all the lists? So the other three, who knows,
depending on who you're reading? Sometimes one of those is Sam El. He's more common on the list
in second-temple Jewish writings, then in.
Christian writings, but as late as St. Gregory the Deologist, at the end of the
six-century AD, you do find him on some Christian lists of the seven archangels.
And so as we've talked about before, don't confuse those seven archangels with
the rank of archangel. When we talked about the nine ranks of the angels.
This is kind of an elite group.
Right. Because arc or
Arch can just mean high or important or
Right like the way we use it with archbishop or arch priest or
right
It's so that could be given as a title to an angel of any rank the archangel Michael for example is identified in the cynic
Sorry and is being a seraphim
So in terms of ranks, right
say it's my calling.
Gabriel are not low ranking in terms of the died ranks of angels.
Right.
Yeah.
So this is saying he's one of those.
Right.
He's one of those.
So when you hear things about the tradition, this is the traditions about Satan being a fallen archangel or coming out of this.
Right, coming out of this.
of traditions. And so it's also I've sometimes heard people say, right, oh well the devil was just
an archangel that's relatively low ranking. No that's not what's being talked about. Yeah the
idea is that he's one of these the highest top gods. Yeah yeah yeah yeah. And so Sam El,
having to name the poison of God, right? Kind of a tell. But the idea was not that...
that he was somehow like always evil or didn't experience a fall or what
have you, it's that he was the angelic being who sort of did the dirty work.
Yeah, which I mean this introduces all kinds of ambiguous problems, right?
Like from our modern perspective.
Yeah, especially not just from a modern perspective, but also from the from
Like if you're thinking about the angels as created beings, created good, and so forth,
the idea that God would create an angel of death, that means that there's a world in which
death is a thing, right?
So it's kind of, it's on the line, right?
without the transgression of Adam, you know, humans don't die.
So is he the angel of death before that happens after that?
Well, it's not like God didn't know what would happen.
Yeah, exactly.
Angels and you don't know what it's like to be.
Yes.
So there's kind of like the sense that this is sort of God's assassin.
But then there's also...
Well, or, you know, first born of Egypt are going to get killed.
I mean, these are actual examples of the Samin.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Although, although...
You do it in your church.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Like if there's a bad thing that needs to happen, there's this...
There are these traditions that Samuels, the one sent from God to go make it happen.
To go do it.
Yeah.
The destroyer, go wipe out the Assyrian RNA.
And it's kind of ambiguous with this concept that we've talked about a bunch of times now,
which is this concept of the left hand of God, which is demons doing their will, fallen angels
doing their will, which is hateful and bad and evil, and yet God has them on a leash.
And so they effectively do God's will, even while they're doing their own will.
Right.
which is the
picture you see of the Satan in Job, right?
Right.
On a leash.
He wants to do all this stuff to Joe,
but he has to kind of go get permission from God.
And then God says, okay, you could do XYZ, but not ABC.
Yeah.
So it's a little ambiguous as to exactly what
Somal where he lands on the left right.
Question.
This is why you'll see, why you'll
see in scholarship at other places, people saying,
Well, enjoy.
I'd pre-Christian Jewish thought Satan was an evil.
Like he sort of works for God.
This is what they're referring to.
So they're not referring to the devil traditions we just talked about.
Like the serpent in the garden and that kind of thing.
They're talking about this Satan figure, the Sam El figure,
Angel of Death figure, the destroyer.
Abaddon's Flash of Paulion in Revelation.
Uh
So that's what that is about.
And so there's kind of a disjunction in the way that's filtered through to popular thinking
now, where they think like, Satan was an okay guy and he was like a cool guy and then Christians turned
into the devil. No, right? That's
woefully an accurate, right?
So there's this figure who's doing these dirty jobs and one of those dirty jobs is
accusing people of sin and trying to put people to the test and
arguing against people's sanctity. He's also set up so within... so there's the
seven archangels, the seven spirits who stand before the earth.
of God and within second-table Jewish thought. And some of this is even reflected in the Hebrew
scriptures in the latter portions because some of those come from the second-table period.
But like in Daniel, as we've talked about before, he talks about, you know, say,
say, Michael having to battle the Prince of Persia and then the Prince of Greece is coming,
talking about these angelic beings who are sort of the angels over a nation.
And of course, St. Michael is presented there in Daniel as being the sort of guardian angel
of Israel, right?
Sort of the patron angel of Israel or at that point, Judah.
But beyond that, these seven, spirits, these seven archangels were in some of the second
double Jewish tax assigned to all of the nations descended from Abraham.
They're sort of parceled out right into the Nivered Age.
So the Edomites, the Amonites, the Roman Empire.
Reminder everyone.
There are other nations besides Israel descended from Abraham.
Right.
Other Abrahamites.
And within that, Simeil is usually presented as the angel assigned to the Edomites.
their descendants of Esa.
Right. And you have to remember when we're talking about the second temple period,
we're talking about the destruction of the first temple, the second temple period,
there's this great enmity between the Itamites and the Israelites that there wasn't always
throughout their history. Yeah, so you can kind of certainly wasn't that point.
You can kind of see where Israelites might be inclined to say that the guardian angel of the Itamites
This is the Angel of Death.
Yes, yes.
And, relatedly then, you get within second-table Jewish writings these clashes between St. Michael and Samuel.
And often, those don't take the form of sort of, I know we'd like to Frank Paretti this and have them be in a cool sword fight or something.
Right.
That's the first of a Ferd Frank Pretty.
uses a verb.
Right.
I'm a word.
Yeah, but it's just, it's not how things work.
Right.
Yes.
If sex, snider, it gets a hold of it.
It will be how things work.
But until then, that's not how things work.
It'll be some freaky movies.
It's a clash in the sense of, say,
it's a Michael defending and semial accusing.
Yeah, it's almost, I mean, in some ways,
It's almost like...
Like a courtroom, right? You've got a prosecutor and you've got to get it.
Well, it's God is king, right? Hearing a case, right? Yeah. Okay. It's like the king hearing a dispute, right?
Between right two parties, right? And so St. Michael is sort of defending, you know, and this is where the idea that we talked about last time in terms of the assumption of Moses, the idea of St. Michael and
Satan
Right. Contesting over the body of Moses comes from.
Yeah. Yeah. This is a pre-existing tradition that they do that kind of thing.
Yeah. That Satan is coming and making accusations against Moses for his sins
and the St. Michael is defending him. Right. Against those accusations.
So then what about where Jesus says that he sees Satan fall like lightning
And yet like yeah, so what do we do with that?
Right so
Yeah, which is in Luke 10 versus 17 through 20
Right
And it's interesting
Because when you read most modern interpreters reading that passage
They've got Miltonian presuppositions.
Right. Yeah, like they'll read it as as Jesus saying, oh, hey, you guys by the way way back before whatever whatever I
Was created I was there remember you guys, you know, I was there. I saw Satan fall like lightning
You know, yeah, which kind of makes it a weird out of
Context comment. Yeah, because the the narrative context is that he's just sent out in this case the 72 apostles
and they come back saying hey we're able to cast out demons.
And he says, and then he responds, I saw Satan fall like lightning, behold, I've given
you authority to tread on serpents and scorpions over all the power of the enemy.
Nothing so hurts you.
That's he's responding to them, talking about being able to do exorcisms about something
that just happened.
Right.
And so seems most likely that Christ is talking about what just happened.
Although.
Christ knows more about it because 72 kept see the spiritual realm and what's going on there.
Right? They're not undergoing an apocalypse at the moment. They're not having a vision, right?
Of course, Christ being God knows right everything that's going on. And when you read all of the early
interpreters of that text, the church fathers, they all interpreted as something that happened
right there.
They all read it that way.
Saved and never heard of John Noen.
And so very interestingly, when you get to Revelation 12,
chapter 12 of the apocalypse of St. John,
and there may be some folks out there who haven't heard us talk about this material before,
or especially who are wondering why we haven't talked about
revelation.
chapter 12 yet, right? Because that of course talks about the dragon being cast out of heaven by
Saint Michael and his angels, right? And that's the passage that's talking about the fall of the
devil. And we didn't talk about it when we talked about the fall of the devil, right? And that's
the passage that people will quote, right? Whether they're trying to defend sort of Milton's view,
they'll be like, no, that's in the Bible.
You're looking...
Revelation 12. This is what that verse says just to review. It says, and the great dragon was thrown
down that ancient serpent who is called the devil and Satan, the deceiver of the whole world. He was
thrown down to the earth and his angels were thrown down with him. Yeah, that's verse 9. That's
That's first time, yeah.
That's where it's not.
So importantly, it context, right?
And if you want sort of...
the earliest Eastern interpreter of this,
whose view of relations has been enshrined
basically the Orthodox Church because it's because of him
that the book of Revelation is canonical in the East.
Essentially, the reason why it's written, why,
why even the limited amount of public reading it has in the East, it has.
It's because of St. Andrew of Cessaria. I know there's some ambiguity about whether he's a saint.
Okay, whatever.
He's a saint, sue me.
That would be an interesting little suit.
Like, is that controversial?
Like, nobody thinks he was a hair-chick or anything.
Right.
It's just like, I don't know.
Is he technically on somebody's calendar?
Yeah.
I mean, if you read, and as I recall, this is how he...
I mean, if you just read the chapter, right?
In verse one, I've just read it.
What you can see is, says, you know, there's this great sign
There's this great sign that appears...
and heaven a woman clothed with the sun, she gives birth,
you know, this great beast arises,
you know, the dragon tries to swallow up the child
to whom she's given birth, she flees in the wilderness,
and then it says, now we're a rose in heaven,
Michael and his angels fighting against the dragon
and then the dragon gets thrown down.
So, however you interpret the first six verses, okay?
And you can interpret it like there's a couple different ways.
As I recall, Andrew Siserie interprets that
being about.
the church, and you know that the church is giving birth to Christ, right?
And so he reads in this kind of spiritual reading, like each one of us has to give birth to
Christ within ourselves, right?
But you could also read it more in terms of, and I don't think this was his reading, but
a perfectly reasonable reading.
And certainly like this has appeared in iconography for sure, is that the woman is the Theotokos,
of course the tailtocus is very closely
associated with the church in many, many cases.
Many such cases.
And Israel.
Yeah, and Israel, right?
And that the church, the child, is Christ.
So however you interpret it, whichever
those sorts of images and narratives you pick,
when the dragon gets thrown down happens after that.
After the birth of Christ.
After the birth of Christ, or after at least the first one,
ever the first one.
Or whatever, it's not some primordial thing.
And it's not even, this is not even in Genesis 3, you know, or is it, right?
Like obviously it's partaking in the same imagery, but clearly it's happening in a different
narrative structure.
Right.
So very clearly, it kind of is, yeah, it's very clearly it's not, doesn't support
Milton.
We'll put it that way.
Yeah.
Yeah, this is not a part of Jesus is born.
That doesn't make any sense.
or other sets and then we roll back to...
before the creation of the world. That doesn't make any sense. That's a reading of revelation in
context. And Saint Andrew says that. He says, first this is presented as being after the birth of
Christ, right? And he says, but we must accept what all the fathers
say, I'm going to say an ended out, when all the fathers say that after the creation of
the world, the devil fell through envy. So the problem for him, right? He's never heard
of John Milton. The problem for him is, well, wait, all the fathers say that the devil
fell right after the creation of the world. But this is talking about Satan falling after
the birth of Christ.
So that's the issue he he feels like he needs to resolve but potentially there's two different figures or
Right one figure whose falls more than once. So he points to he does sort of the end indeed right he quotes Luke 10 17 through 20
Right Christ said at that point which was after his birth right that
that
He saw Satan fall like lightning at that time
time.
And so then he says, well, you've got two options.
You've got two options.
You've got one figure here who fell in one sense
after the creation of the world and fell in another sense
because fell is kind of a flexible verb here.
Right.
Fell in another sense during the life of Jesus
that Jesus is referring to in Luke 10.
or or
We've got two different figures here, each of which fall once.
And how would you get the two different figures?
Well, as Father Andrew read in Revelation 12, 9,
it's that ancient serpent.
Okay, so that's talking about the Genesis 3, dude, right?
The serpent, who is called the devil.
Right?
So that's the devil.
And Satan, the deceiver of the whole world.
Yeah, or you can read.
So that ancient serpent who is called the devil and Satan.
Right.
So is he called the devil and Satan or is it the serpent who is called the devil and
Satan?
Right. There's other dude. Yeah. And Andrew says to Rhea says you can read it in
in both ways which now he reads it as being one figure who falls twice. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Right.
He doesn't read it as two separate figures but he reads it as
one figure who falls twice in two different senses. And so the names then for him are
referring to the two different senses. Yeah. But devil is referring to that first fall.
And Satan is referring to this second one. To me, this underlines a couple of things.
One is that the way that the church fathers read scripture is not in a sense of, and I
don't know, I'm going to hammer this again. Even though we've hammered 100 times, I think
It's worth it to hammer this again.
There's not a sense of
like what's the Bible code?
This verse means this thing
and we have to figure out what this one thing
that it means is.
There are multiple possibilities.
Even with things like this,
which are maybe, I don't know, questions of fact,
is this one figure or two figures?
That's theoretically one of those
is true and the other is not.
I don't know.
Although we'll get to that.
Or they're both not true and there's three.
Yeah.
But then the other thing,
and this is raised by this question,
especially if you accept it as a single figure falling twice,
is what exactly is a fall.
Because I think that especially kind of in, I don't know, pop Christian theology just
come very common.
The idea is that a fall means that that's the moment that this being turns to evil, right?
So when we think of the fall of Adam, he turns to evil, you know, that's how that often is used.
But actually the scripture is a little bit more literal.
I mean, it's not utterly literal, but it's more literal with using the word fall,
about being thrown out of somewhere.
You know thrown out of heaven, thrown out of the garden, thrown out.
And right.
And because if you use it as turned to evil, does that mean Adam then repented and then
fell again the next time he sinned?
Or that the devil repented and then turned again, you know, like way to be.
Right.
So that obviously isn't what it means.
Because we would say with the expulsion from paradise, that's why I tend to use that language
rather than fall of man I talk about the expulsion from
paradise because it's more specific, right?
What we're talking about, right?
That is very different than just
the cycle of sinning and repenting,
which we can analogize to falling and getting back up.
Sure, sure.
Right.
But there is something unique,
paradigmatic about the expulsion for paradise
in terms of its effect on all humanity
that is different than just Adam sinning
and repenting over the course of the rest of his life,
For example.
Right, there's a differentiation there.
Right, we're not talking about the same thing.
Right, and so the idea then is that if those two titles refer to ways in which the
devil fell, the idea would be if it's one figure that the devil is right cast into the underworld,
Vabler the dead all that in Genesis 3, right, but is still able to
at times come into like in the book of Job, Satan is able to come in and act as the
Satan, right? To fulfill this role, to accuse. And in fact if you read Revelation 12
verse 10, the very next verse, he's referred to as the accuser of the brethren,
as the accuser of the brethren. That's what we see him doing with the body of
Moses, the body of Moses there, kind of representing Israel.
also beyond just Moses himself, but he's the accuser of Israel, St. Michael's defending Israel.
The Israelites, the Judahites, right, the people of God.
And so the idea is that in the ministry of Christ and his disciples and apostles,
he loses this role as the saint. That there's now no one to make an accusation
against God's people.
And it's interesting, I mean, I can verse 11 there of Revelation 12, right after it calls
them the accuser.
And of course it says, who accuses them day and night before our God, right?
So it's clearly that that's the context as you're accusing them to God.
And then it says, and they, that's the brethren, have conquered him by the blood of the Lamb
and by the word of their testimony for their love, not their lives, even unto death.
the scenes have conquered the accuser here in Revelation.
Right. Right. So there's now no accusation. And this is by the way, this is what St. Paul is referring to.
I know sorry, sorry Calvinists, we have to have at least one in episode. Yes.
Certain folks are just desperate to make it so that there's all this forensic language in Romans and in St. Paul's other epistles.
This is all courtroom stuff. This is all courtroom stuff. It's not, none of it is.
The closest you get is him making references to this dynamic when he talks about no one being able to make an accusation against God's elect and that kind of thing
That's what he's talking about. He's talking about the devil no longer being able to
Make it accuse God's people
Because of what Christ did
All right, well, it's not talking about the last judgment or being
Judge righteous
It's just, it's not there.
Yeah.
Well, you don't want to be judged by Satan.
No one is judged by Satan.
Exactly.
That's the whole point.
Yeah.
All right, well, that's our, the first half of our mega episode on the devil.
We talked about the devil and Satan.
And there's a lot more devilishness to come.
So we'll be right back with the next half of the Lord of Spirits.
Plane.
your wedding and reception can seem overwhelming with countless details hijacking your time
and energy.
In the book Crowned and Orthodox Christian Wedding Guide, author Christopher Dorechak and
Delaney Claude Felter help you identify your big three priorities to guide your decisions
while keeping the emphasis on marriage as an Orthodox Christian sacrament.
Use this resource to help you simplify the process and keep Christ at the center of your
wedding day.
available at store.inchantfaith.com.
Again, that is store.inchantfaith.com.
And we're back.
It's the second half of this pre-recorded episode
of the Lord of Screed's podcast.
We're talking about the devil, zzzz.
And in the first half, we discussed the devil and the Satan,
and which are probably the names that most people are
familiar with figures.
like this. And now we're going to start discussing some names that are less familiar.
But of course, if you've been listening to this podcast for a long time, you probably
heard, not probably all of them, I think actually it would put her another, some with more
detail than others. So as we mentioned in the beginning, some of this will be review in
the sense of, we've talked about some of these figures before, but this is kind of from
a different, a different angle, a different context, right? So, all right. So we got up
next in terms of our diabolic.
who's on deck?
Yes, the official handbook of the Lord of Spirits Universe.
Yeah, so yeah.
So these next few of the second half are maybe less well known outside of the Lord of Spirits
Universe.
Yes, right.
Your average person has heard of the devil in Satan, but maybe not some of these folks.
And so the first one is probably the most major figure at second tip.
Jewish literature who has the least mention in the canonical scriptures. Not none, but the least
like direct, obvious mention, and that's a zeal. Now, if you're not in the Lord's Spirit's
expanded universe, but you've seen fallen with Denzel Washington, then you may know about a zeal.
but otherwise probably not so much.
Whereas, where the name occurs, I should say, in the canonical scriptures is first in the,
and later on when it is mentioned, it is in the context of the Day of Atonement,
rituals described in Leviticus chapter 16.
Yeah, and the word is actually used there, although often it's hidden underneath translation.
Right, we're going to talk about that here in a minute.
Yeah, so you have the two goats who are used in the David Oetman ritual and you cast lots
so that one of these goats will be designated as the goat for Yahweh and the other one in
the Hebrew as the goat for a Zazel.
And the goat for Yahweh gets offered up as a sacrifice to him.
Right, a sin offering in particular, and that the blood is taken and used to purify the physical accoutrements of the tabernacle.
And then later the temple to make atonement for a bunch of inanimate objects. But we're not going to go into atonement stuff here per se.
Yeah, I mean, check out our episode called The Priest shall make atonement, which is about all of that.
In great detail.
So the question.
that is who is this a Zazel figure. So a Zazel can be translated based on Aazel being the word for
goat as the goat who goes away. Yeah the three get this translation of scape goat. Yes, scape is in a
scape. So the goat who goes away. And that is the basis for most English translations.
not all some will put
of the Z-Zel now, but most single translations have scapegoat, or some derivative thereof,
interpreting it as the goat who goes away.
But there's sort of a problem here in that translation.
In that the language in the Hebrew is completely parallel.
There's a goat for Yahweh and a goat for a Z-Zel.
And so goat for Yahweh means Yahweh's name, one of his names.
This is the goat.
for him, the goat that belongs to him.
Right.
And then you're saying,
even though the language is totally parallel,
that the second one is,
this is the goat for the goat that goes away.
Yeah.
So I should point out by the way
that like the earliest known use of scapegoat
in English is in,
is a translation of this passage by Tindale.
So it's one of the earliest English b-
and basically tend to invent the word to translate a Zazel.
He was beyond that, like atonement.
Yeah.
So, yeah, so that parallel doesn't work.
Right?
Of, wait a second.
a name and this is like I guess a role that you
choosing the go for? Like you're not choosing the first goat to be God obviously.
Right? It is his, it's given to him. Right? And then the second goat you're saying then is
you're choosing it to be a scapegoat. Right? So the fact that the language is perfectly parallel
doesn't make, it isn't reflected by that translation. Kind of doesn't make sense. Then you also
to factor in the fact that every...
Second-templed Jewish interpretation we have.
All of the earliest outside Hebrew Scriptures literature we have,
from Jewish sources interpreting the name of Zazel,
it all interpreted as being a demonic spirit.
Yeah, and that might lead you to think, by the way,
if you know anything about stuff we've said earlier,
about names of spirits, that Zazel,
that that EL on the end is a Theophoric,
because L is God.
It's not, it's as equally a false friend.
It's not actually, it's not L.
Yes.
Azo is goat.
It has nothing to do with L as in God.
So yeah.
So it treats it as a name.
And that, right, that way of reading it
makes sense with the actual Hebrew
whether you have this parallel.
Yahweh is a name.
So as Azo is a name, right.
So that makes it important the fact that
while this is it.
as you read the ritual, where the one goat is sacrificed to Yahweh, and the other goat
is sacrificed to Azazel. It is not sacrificed to Azazel.
Yeah, it's clear if you read the instructions, again, read the text of Ithaca 16, that the
actions done to the goat for Yahweh are actions of sacrifice. You know, putting it on an
altar and all that sort of stuff. But then the goat for Azazel is sent away into the wilderness.
is a
as it says in place.
It's not sacrificed, it is not killed.
So I will digress, I have to, right?
Sorry, penal substitutionary atonement supporters.
The only time in the scriptures where sin is put on an animal,
it's not sacrificed, it's not even killed.
And this is the only time checking for yourself and see
that there's no other place where sins are put on an animal.
And of course it makes sense because once you put...
sins on the animal, it's unclean. Yeah, you don't, you can't sacrifice something unclean
to God. Yeah, that's not a thing. And you're not going to sacrifice to something other than
God. Right. Let's go. It's not sacrifice. That would be idolatry, everybody. Right. And
because of the identifier with this asal, you can't get around this. Looking at you, William
Lane Craig in your response to me online.
can't get around this by saying that in some weird metaphorical sense, the scapegoat
is sacrificed because if it were, it would be being sacrificed to a zeal.
Right.
Like, that is, that is sin number one.
You don't want to say that.
Yes.
Sin number one in the scriptures.
Right.
Yeah.
You don't want to have sacrificing things to a demon in your atonement theory, my friend.
So yeah, like there's just, this is where...
Atonement is sort of described and defined for the whole rest of the Bible here at the Torah and an
Ain't people substitutionary atonement that makes no sense with it. So sorry guys
Another dog that don't hunt
Another factor in terms of understanding
why
universally the original interpreters understood as asal as being a demonic spirit is
is Leviticus 17 verse.
So remember chapter 16 is where the J- if it's only 17 verse 7, so there's just a few verses later after the end of the description of the day of atonement.
God says that they will no longer worship the goat spirit or goat demon in some translations of the wilderness.
Remember the name of Zazel is built around the word for goat.
So these early interpreters are looking at the immediate context and saying, oh!
Azazel is this goat spirit of the wilderness, right? This demonic spirit of the wilderness, the desert outside the camp.
It's explicitly saying there you will no longer worship them. He can't be telling them to sacrifice a goat to it.
even if you thought that was somehow possible.
And so it's not just that, oh this is...
right? Goat Lord of the Desert. It's, right, the idea is the wilderness is the
wilderness around the Israelite camp. We've talked about these concentric
circles, right, that are of holiness, working their way out from the tabernacle.
But the camp is the end of those, right? Outside of the Israelite camp, this island,
right? There's the rest of the world is under the curse.
under the control of evil spiritual powers. And Azazel is sort of seen in this idea as
being the head of all of those, as being sort of the big bad, the devil, right, in that
sense, right, of this supreme evil being, is this evil power over the surrounding world
outside the camp.
Yeah, there's this, I mean, and you know, this is really a common idea in a lot of, especially
modern cultures where...
travel is just a dangerous thing to do. You know, I mean, people did it, but it was
always regarded as dangerous and that sense of the the surrounding world being
kind of evil and chaotic and full of death and it's not just because there's
bandits out there. You know, or even just that there's wild animals or natural
naturally dangerous terrain or whatever. Like there's the sense that it's ruled
by the
sort of spirits. I mean, this is like the basis for the Grendel image in Beowulf, you know,
the dark thing that's out there somewhere. Right. Right. And so, and, and by the way,
before we move too far, I know there's someone out there going, well, they, they, you said they
didn't kill it, but they shoved it off a cliff, right? First of all, it's not in Leviticus 16.
Yeah, meaning it's not part of the ritual.
That is something that they started doing at some were not sure when, exactly when, but
they started doing it some point later in the second temple period.
But was not universally done, by the way, because, for example, when the epistle of Varnibus
in the first century talks about the day of Atonement ritual, it gives a lot of details
about how it was practiced.
Little details beyond what's in Leviticus 16 of particular practices regarding it in
Jerusalem in the first century.
It talks about it being let out and tied to a bush.
Not shoved off a cliff.
Though we know there was a period where they were shoving it off a cliff.
But both tying it to the bush and shoving it off the cliff that are to the Vitica 16, right?
These are practical issues.
Because what do you do when you lead the sin go out of the camp with all your sins and evil on it?
And it comes wandering back into town.
Yeah.
Get that thing out of here.
Right, like yeah, go right, right so
So they started taking things to make sure that didn't make sure it wasn't able to do
that.
But they're different means at different times and it's not part of the ritual per se.
The idea and the ritual is that as aesol, the evil spirits out there, they're sort of
the ultimate source of sin and corruption and wickedness that they've like lured humans
into.
And so you're putting the same...
on the goat and then stamping it return to sender.
Like you're sending it back where it came from.
Yeah, the goat is a transport mechanism
to send the sins out so they don't longer corrupt the camp.
It's carrying them away, right?
And then even fits with eventually
like pushing it off a cliff, right?
Because where ultimately are those spirits?
They're in the underworld.
Right, so you push it into a crag in the ground, right?
then I mean that's mean to the poor.
You know, imagine the poor goat, right?
Like that goat did do anything.
On the other hand, he got to live.
The other one got killed and sacrificed.
So, you know, from a goat's perspective, you know,
I don't know which one you'd want to be necessary.
You know, goat tastes good.
I know that.
Goat tastes good.
Yeah, curry goat is awesome.
Yeah, so you're returning it back to Azazel.
And
So then you get sort of imagery surrounding his asal.
And I mean that quite literally in terms of his appearance,
what his appearance is described.
As we move into now,
how Second Temple Literature talks about him as a figure, right?
We're moving now.
That's pretty much where he's directly talked about
by name in the scripture.
We're gonna talk about here.
There are some new testament references to him.
And Second Temple Literature will read Azazel
back into.
some preceding stories before Leviticus 16.
But in terms of where he's mentioned by name and directly,
obviously this is talking about his asal, that's pretty much it.
Leviticus 16 and that one verse and 17 referring to the Ghost Spirit of the Wilderness.
But as the figure gets developed,
these patterns get developed that we talked about before in Second Temple Literature,
He's described in terms basically that are similar
to what we would now call baffamette,
this depiction of the devil or Satan or this figure as a goat.
Yeah, although it should be noted everybody that that figure,
like at least the earliest mention of that name
is only like 13th century, 14th century maybe,
associated with the night's temple art.
But I mean it's feeding on imagery that has existed for a very,
very, very, very long time.
Right, right.
and is connected not just to this but
to, you know, a Christian circle's Christ
parable the sheep and the goats.
Yeah.
She'd go to heaven goats, go to hell.
Right.
So like Kexat, there's a lot of goat connections there,
right, that play into that goat imagery.
I was just using Baphomet as like an example
that people, maybe you're familiar with now
because they keep wanting to prop up statues and stuff.
I know.
Edge lords.
So.
Yeah, and then the other imagery is him being depicted sort of like a raven.
And ravens being an unclean bird, but specifically being associated with this, when Abraham
had the covenant between...
Well, when the covenant was cut literally to use the Hebrew word,
between God and Abraham. Remember this episode where he splits the
animals into, cuts the animals into, and then the presence of God moves between them.
We've talked about that a show before. We won't go into it now. But in that episode, right,
Abraham has to sort of beat off these scavenger birds who come for the
halved animals while they're laying there. Right? As one might expect, right? What happened?
But those birds that Abraham has to sort of shoo away.
associated with sort of the idea that there's these evil spirits trying to break
the covenant between humanity and God. Right? Well, how can they do that? Well,
they can't break it from God's end, but they get kind of get humans to. Right?
They can lure humans into violating it. Right? But so because of that, he gets this sort
of Raven Bird, Scaminger Bird.
imagery associated with him in his description sometimes.
Like, he'll tell me about having wings and feathers and stuff.
That's what I mean.
Quite literally that imagery.
So in Second Temple Jewish literature,
there's both, as I mentioned, this sort of retrospective
putting Azazel back into earlier parts,
specifically Genesis of the Torah.
And then also...
sort of this eschatological element.
So both sort of, Azazel's been the problem from the beginning,
and then also how Azazel's going to be finally dealt with in the end.
Right, gets sort of fleshed out.
And this is across a number of works.
In second-tip literature, this even includes, and there are some references to these ideas
in...
the, the, the New Testament, including, especially in, in the Johanning literature.
But so starting with that retrojection and get excited people, here it comes.
Right. So we've talked a lot before obviously and we're, we're going to be brief with it this time because again, not only have we talked about it a bunch, but I think by far
our most listen
two episodes is the giant's episode. People go back to it all the time. So, right, we don't need to spend a ton of time here rehashing all that. But, so, there is this sort of expansion in detailing more of the story of Kane's line, his lineage, his genealogy leading up to the flood. Right, it starts in Genesis 4.
And that involves the idea that Keynes descendants were involved, described as sexual involvement,
with angelic powers who fell in the process, who turned to evil in the process.
And as part of that relationship gained knowledge.
of what we would call technology, but beyond what we would call technology, sort of spiritual
technology like sorcery, or sinful, like seduction, these sorts of things.
And within Keynes line in Genesis, you see Tuble Kane is descendant and his sons who start
you
livestock for me and metallurgy to make weapons and these kind of things.
There's an expansion on that.
And we've talked about how this is parallel, right?
This expansion of what's going on in Genesis is really interpreting it in light once again
of a pagan story or a series of whole set of pagan stories, which are again, not ultimately
just stories but are part of their
religious life. This is another critique where we're getting the true story in Genesis over
against the story that the nations tell and who they're worshiping. And a particularly
good example of that is the Apkalu story that we've talked about. It's reflected in the
Sumerian Kings list, the story of the Seven Sages, where you have these pre-Flood kings
in the Sumerian king list who each have an upkalu this sort of
divine being as their advisor and then after the flood all of these kings are two-thirds
up-caloo. Yeah this sense of not only you know mating with them but also like okay this ancient
anti-deluvian knowledge being given to these kings and many cases that's the king's basis for saying
Hey look I have the
balance, therefore, I should rule.
Right. Right. And then that, you know, in the world that leads into the Amarites.
Right. We've talked about that comes from a moonroom, meaning the Westerners,
their particular group that moved in and took over Old Babylon.
Homurabi is the most famous Amarite.
That's outside of Scripture.
their Amorites mentioned there of course and there's sort of
claim to power was that they had retained those antedeluvian pre-flood secrets and knowledge.
So that expansion, the expansion of the scriptures includes not only the expansion of the scriptures
fleshing out how it relates to this story, includes not only the pre-flood part but also the post-flood part
in that it includes also the interpretation of Genesis 6.
sons of God and the daughters of men, and then their children, right? The Nephilim,
the Giants, or the Tyrants, or the bullies. Again, giant episode, we talk about this
several times. Ogg, King of Bashan being an example, Deuteronomy 311 talks about
the size of his bed, right, presenting him as a giant. And that has to do with, as
you've talked about on the show before the pagan ritual.
rituals in which many of these kings were sired in sort of a literal sense where you would
have a temple prostitute or the current king sort of embodying a divinity in terms of
from our perspective, you know, possession essentially. And then through sexual,
Congress.
producing a child that they then believed.
Essentially had three parents, the deity, the king,
and the human woman, which made them two thirds divine,
because of course they thought the king was divine.
And one third human, like the two thirds of Kalo,
and this is sort of the origin of these pagan kings.
And so the fleshed out version, right,
It's excellent.
explaining how the narrative of Genesis relates to those pagan stories is really
fleshing out the fact that it is again running counter to them. So this was, this
was what made these kings glorious. This is what made this age a golden age from
the perspective of pagan religion. From the perspective of the Scriptures made
especially clear by this fleshing out in Second Temple literature. This was a
A period of horror
and evil and these kings were tyrants.
And engage in the whole matter of evil.
A story that some people might be aware of
that feeds into all of this is the Atlantis story,
which is a story of about a civilization,
a great massive technologically advanced civilization
that gets drowned.
And if someone says, oh, I have this ancient knowledge
from Atlantis, like, ooh, you know,
a lot of people don't know
you actually read it.
the Atlantis myths, you know, as it's detailed in Plato and stuff, is the people who run the
place are all children of Poseidon. So there's this, there is this, there's this, there's
giants basically there's this idea that they are the result of human and divine, you know,
intermingling. Right. So that's, that's all, like, that's a very familiar story that actually
just feeds into all of these patterns that we just talked about.
Right.
And, and, Prometheus.
Yeah.
Right, over and over again, right?
Pick your ancient Near Eastern civilization.
There's all different versions of this idea,
which is being very clearly called evil.
And we have to distinguish here also,
there's two different groups that's gonna become important
in a minute once we're done with the Zazel.
You've got these angelic beings who sort of initiate this.
Right, who are associated, for example,
with the Titans very often,
including by St. Peter.
in Second Peter with the Titans in Greek myth,
who are then for their crimes sort of imprisoned
by the other gods, usually somewhere.
The Epochalus story, they're imprisoned in the Abyss,
which is under the Euphrates River.
I mean, I was just permithious, right?
We know about, I could say,
to Iraq with a culture eating as a liver.
But they're punished in some way, right?
and then...
in the second-table Jewish literature, right?
They're generally imprisoned in the abyss, right?
Or what have you?
And Azazel is the leader of these.
He sort of-
Azazel is one of these angels who sort of sets this in process.
Yeah, I don't want to quite say he's like retconned
into all of these stories, but that's kind of the best way
to understand it, I think.
Yeah, well, no, he is retconned.
like he sees I dead or he's identified as being the figure.
Right, he's the leader of them.
So in the book of Enoch, he holds this meeting.
He calls these other angels together,
these other angelic beings together on Mount Hermann,
and forms this pact with them to go seduce human women,
to teach them their secrets and everything.
So it's Azo's leader.
So it's Azo's leader of that group.
Right, and then there are sort of the first round of nephilum,
the first round of giants.
of these tyrant kings who are their children, right? Who are their sons, right? Who are
humans, right? Who are a separate group? Now a lot of them end up suffering the same
fate, but there is a distinction there. Yeah, the father's quote-unquote and the sons
quote-unquote. Yeah, and we'll be talking about the sons more at least briefly here
when we're done with the Zazel.
But there's other there's other retcons too like the apocalypse of Abraham identifies
as Azal as the serpent in Genesis 3. So I mean, yeah. So it's right. All the bad stuff
that was Azal back then. Yeah. And that's an example, by the way, everybody of how sometimes
these various figures get suddenly merged together by one or more of these texts. Yeah.
Yeah. But the apocalypse of Abraham, the first and second Enic do this too. The apocalypse
of Abraham is very much.
focused on the idea that there's going to be an eschatological day of atonement,
whereas Azal is sort of finally taken care of.
Yeah, I mean, if you're talking to Azal's going to come up.
Right.
But so, Apocos of Abraham wants to put him all the way back in Genesis 3 to say,
this guy was always the problem.
Yeah. This guy was the problem from the beginning.
Right, the day of atonement was a way of dealing with him provisionally along the way,
But ultimately
at the end of days he's going to get dealt with once and for all.
Right. Which is why it makes sense to identify Azazel as a The Devil figure.
Right. Right.
That he's the one who has to be dealt with. Right.
And so within, and we talked about this back in our Christology series,
in the Poxillabraha for example, there's this figure, Yo-ho-l, there's this
It's a angel called your H.L. which means basically Yahweh God.
It's his name.
It's the name of it.
So this is an angel of the Lord figure, right?
This is a second person of Yahweh figure, right?
In the apocalypse of Abraham, who is sort of the high priest along with Abraham.
So he's sort of a list Abraham.
To be the high priest in this sort of eschatological day of atonement where,
whereas these will finally get taken care of for good.
And first, the arc angels are sent to go
take care of him, right? But there's still, even in that context, the way they take
care of him is clearly connected to the Day of Atonement ritual. But it is a sort
of eschatological fulfillment of the Day of Atonement where he's finally dealt
with. But so in 1st-Enic 10 verse 8, there's this sort of summary verse. And this
is within that eschatological Day of Atonement idea where he's being kind of
dealt with.
says there that the whole earth has been corrupted by the teaching of the works of
Azazel to him ascribe all sin. So again, all the sin that's ever happened is ultimately
the fruit of Azazel's poison tree. It's the idea there. If we take care of Azazel,
we've taken care of sin once and for all. It's the idea there. That's part of the command
to go.
finally deal with him.
Which I think this is a really important point when you're dealing with this question of,
you know, the Odyssey, right?
The origin of evil and how you deal with it is that there's this sense that the reason
why there's evil in the world is because of demons.
It's because of demons.
And so if you really want to truly get rid of all the evil in the world, you have to
get rid of the demonic influence.
Yeah.
You can't just keep sending it back to him every year.
Purifying things from
every year. You've got to finally just deal with them. And it's not just about humans repenting and
being forgiven either. It's also like you have to deal with the origin of it all this stuff, which
is in this as it says here, Azazel or more broadly demons. Yeah, the devil. How are we going to
sum this up? Yeah, the evil one. Right. Yeah. Also though, note that this whole idea points to
to the idea that the Torah is doing
something provisional in the in between time. So that's not a new idea in the
New Testament. Right? That like the day of Atonement ritual was there as like a
management system and eventually the problem that it was managing the
problem it was dealing with would be ultimately solved. So when the New
Testament writers come along and say yes Jesus is the Messiah and he has
is actually now-
resolve these problems. That's not like an unforeseen thing from a Jewish perspective.
Yeah, it was hoped for. Right. In fact, they were hoping for the Messiah to come and deal with all of
the, whether it was a priestly Messiah or right, however they saw it. We've talked about that before.
Right. They were looking forward to the Messiah coming and finally solving the problems that the Torah
had been managing. But so within that verse we read from
first ennick. You see a bunch of
understandings and interpretations that are born out
elsewhere like Kane as he's presented in
scripture right he sort of wanders off screen
and found the city and has a bunch of kids
and we don't really see much of him
himself right. Reflected there he becomes
bigfoot in Genesis yeah sorry it's my
favorite Mormon legend what could I say?
Oh, that is big quick. Yeah, I mean they don't all believe
that. It's just a thing that goes around to those circles.
Well, he showed up and told that guy in Tennessee, didn't he?
That's that's it's based on that. Yeah, this actually counter 19th century.
Yeah, you had talked to Bigfoot Bigfoot told him he was king.
Well, I think a cane walking the earth, though, I think of quite Chen
K. But anyway,
So but in the broader suite, I would say the broader suite of second-level literature.
I'm including stuff like Josephus, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
See Cain not just as this sort of this guy who did this horrible thing and then had to
muddle through the rest of his life and his kids just got worse and worse before the
flood, but Cain is this active participant in evil throughout his life.
That he was this teacher of evil to his children, that he was a heretic, that he was the right
sort of every bad thing that was cane and cane
was sort of doing this, that's reflected in, I mentioned the Johanian literature in this
sort of, as Aisle ideas, in 1 John 3 verse 12, right, it talks about Cain as being of the wicked one.
Yeah, sort of like that. Of the, say he's the, like the son of, right? It's like he's a Aisle Jr.
Yeah, yeah. He's sort of the embodiment, right, the way that, again, if we see Aisle as being one
one of these parents of the giants, right? The idea here.
that Cain is like one of the sons in that sense, right?
These sort of supremely evil in that sense.
And no, okay, look, look.
You weirdos.
We have a lot of weirdos who listen to this show.
I mean, welcome, weirdo.
I know.
We're happy to have you.
Some of you out there who are such weirdos
that you think even the serpent did something.
Oh, yes, the serpent seed non-gain was not in.
I will tell you, okay, okay, since you brought...
that up. I wasn't going to say anything about this but since you brought it up I visited several
years ago I did a speaking engagement in Louisville, Kentucky and right across the river in
I think it's in Indiana. There's a cemetery there and a church and the church is called the
Brannum Tabernacle and its name for William Brannum and William Brannum was this, he was his mid-20th
in the century faith healer.
And he initially did lots and lots of sort of faith healing, but then he started teaching all these weird, weird things.
And one of the things he taught was this serpent seed idea, which is the idea that Cain is the literal child of the devil and Eve.
And that the origin of evil in the world is this.
There's this sort of race of other humans out there who are literally children of the devil.
of the day.
Yeah.
Canis.
And so what's.
Fun, it, well, maybe fun's not the right word.
I don't know.
I mean, I'm interested in weird religious movements,
especially stuff that's kind of pseudo-Christian.
So what's interesting is, I mean, number one,
if you ever get a chance to go visit the cemetery
you should, because he's got this really weird grave soon.
It's kind of like a pyramid with an eagle on the top.
But not too far away from Branham's grave.
And by the way, like if you visit his grave,
you can find people leaving letters for him
and all kinds of stuff, like his followers visit him.
In fact, every year on East...
or people show up at his grave expecting him to arrive from the dead.
Anyway, not too far away from his grave is one of his followers' graves.
There's actually multiple graves in the cemetery that belong to followers of his.
And you can tell by what's written on their graves.
But one of them is this big, I think it's a cross from this woman who's one of his followers.
And on the back of it, it has this like poem, two William Branham,
and it lists off all of his wackiest teachings, and the serpent seed is there.
It's-
crazy stuff. Anyway, look him up everybody. William Brandham, I think I put a little bit about him in
Orthodoxy and Heterodoxy and the chapter on Pentecostalism and so forth because he's just such an
interesting wacky figure. And there's videos of him on YouTube. You can see him doing his faith
healing thing on YouTube. And unlike a lot of faith hewers today where it's all like big
spectacular show, he's like awkward and it's a little, you know, difficult to watch because he's
It's just not like a good
showmen, but anyway, fascinating weird figure, but he was one he's one of the origins of the
the popularization of the Serpent seed doctrine in America, and there are still brand of my groups
out there who in fact I recently spoke with somebody who ran into someone who belonged to one of
these groups. There's still groups out there that teach this stuff and yeah, yeah, weird weird
Don't do it. Not once. Don't go there.
But there's not a whiff of that in Genesis,
and that's not what St. John is saying here.
No, not even a little bit.
Very clearly.
Yeah.
Right.
Because then the person he murdered wouldn't have been his brother.
Yeah.
So, but as you read,
if you read first John closely,
it becomes apparent that at least these ideas,
that we saw in 1st Dean, 10 verse 8, are there in the background.
1st John does talk about atonement.
We won't go into that here.
I could trust me by dissertation.
But he talks about atonement explicitly.
And so this language is kind of surrounding their makes sense,
if St. John is familiar with broader Second Temple literature,
which he certainly is.
So for example, 1st John 5 verse 19,
he says, the whole world lies under the power of the evil one.
Right, like the whoreth has been corrupted by the teaching of this.
works of his asal. Right. And it's very clear from the way St. John uses the
whole phrase the whole world, Olu Kozmu, that he is referring to like the
material world, which makes sense in terms of atonement. Right? Yeah, you've got to
clean up the space. Yeah. And then first John three verse eight he says that
rise, appeared to destroy the works of the devil. Not to destroy the devil or defeat the
devil, but to destroy the works of the devil, which kind of parallels the works of
Azazel that have corrupted the whole earth. That's simple removal. Those works which
are being done by humans, even though they're the works of this demonic figure, humans
like cane.
So when you look at first enich, what happens to a zazel like the spiritual being or even the apocos of Abraham, this other literature, he's bound and imprisoned in a pit.
And then in first enich, he's freed at the end of days for a brief period and then thrown into a lake of fire.
That's how familiar to anybody.
So, it was what happens in the book of Revelation.
to the devil. Right. And so, and that, of course, plays all the language we say about
Paska, sent into Hades, Christ binding the devil. Right. All of that is a pattern that we
find in the Azazel descriptions in Second Temple Jewish literature. Right. So moving from
you're a
the fathers to the sons. And we're not going to spend too much time on
mastima. Yeah, because we just covered a whole bunch about him in the Jubilee's
episode to episode two. Jubilee's episode. So you could get more detail there.
Right. And that was like, well, when you hear this, that'll be what like four
weeks ago. Um, yeah, so yeah, you could go back and listen to that one. That's not
that long ago. Um, don't have a ton new to say about mastima, to be honest. Yeah.
Bye.
briefly as we talked about there, he was sort of the leader of the pre-flood giants.
And he's the one who, once they're all wiped out, and they're all now bodyless spirits,
they're about to get thrown into the abyss too, just like their quote-unquote parents.
He comes and cuts the deal with God where 10% of them can stick around to torment the wicked
and the other 90%.
Right. Sorry guys. The best for you.
And then, uh,
God allows that he accepts the deal because he's going to use their tormenting of the wicked to bring them to repentance.
This is explaining the phenomenon that we see like with Saul, the king when the unclean spirit enters into him to torment him.
Yeah, and they're called unclean because it's this idea that they're in some way
result of a mixing hybridization between angels and humans.
Again, we're not saying that that literally happens.
Right.
I'm talking about DNA.
Yeah.
Because the scriptures aren't talking about DNA.
Yeah, we're saying that the book of the unique isn't even
talking about DNA.
This is the way the imagery is presented.
Right.
OK.
And then, of course, Tobit, we see another demon.
And then the exorcisms that we see
across, like the synoptic gospels of the Book of Acts.
These disembodied, formerly demonized human spirits, right, that become demons.
And it's Sir St. John Chrysostom quote here.
Yes.
You could go back and listen to that.
We've given it several times to certain people's consternation.
And it is in the Lord of Spirits book.
That how do you're shilling for?
your book. I mean, if there's going to be anywhere I'm going to mention the book, this
is the show where I'm going to do it. Is there anywhere you're not going to mention
the book? Yes. I don't, I don't try to sell it to my wife, for instance. She could just
get it out of the box as I have in the basement. Yes, exactly. But you do mention it, I bet.
Not that often. Although one of my sons is reading it. So if I asked your wife, how
often would she think you bring it up? I probably...
more often than I think.
Yeah, exactly.
But yeah, yeah.
So, but, and you know, mastimas an interesting figure for a bunch of reasons, again, see the
Jubilee's episode.
But what makes him particularly different from all these other guys that we've been talking
about is that unlike the rest, he's not depicted as a fallen angel figure.
He rather is basically a truly fallen human because he's
one of the giants and what is a giant is simply a truly demonized human. So he's a disembodied,
demonized human. He functions in like a demon. Yeah. Yeah. He functions in the way that St. John
Christophe says that it is possible for humans. You know? Yes. Yeah. Which is the flip side of the
the sons of the resurrection as Christ says, it's at Luke's gospel being
of God equal to the angels. The flip side of that is being like an even.
So the last sort of major individual figure, and we've talked about this, we talked about
him a couple of times briefly. Most recently, the last episode, we talked about him briefly,
as he shows up at the Ascension of Isaiah.
And that's Balael.
sometimes belly are due to airomatic dialects and pronunciations. And Belyl, of course,
as we mentioned already in that episode, I think at least briefly comes from the airomatic
belly-ol. Most people agree now. I mean, the journal articles got to be published
everything but most people agree comes from belly all which means
Yo-k-l-s
just the equates. Yes, that's exactly what I mean. He is meringue. Anyway, the meringue demon.
Yes. Light, fluffy, deadly. This is going to become a t-shirt. I hope. Yeah, yes, I do want to see the...
I mean they made a horror movie about an evil demon possessed pair of jeans.
anything is possible people. The yolk, no, it is a yolkless without a yolk.
Like a wild bull or wild ox who does not have a yolk. Yeah. The lawless one.
He's out of control. Yoke here referring to the Torah, the lawless being lawless,
uncontrolled. And this is.
is a title that's used all over the place.
We're gonna give some examples here in a second
from books we've recently talked about in fact,
all across Second Temple literature,
when it talks about the Messiah,
and when the Messiah comes,
and it talks about there being an enemy of his,
so it's the Messiah versus, right?
The name that's used over and over and over again is Balael.
The Messiah over-
against Boliol. So the Melchizedek scroll, right, in the Dead Sea scrolls, it's
Melchizedek and all the righteous gods versus Boliol and all the gods of evil.
Right, that's lower G gods, right, referring to angels and saints in the one case
and folks like Mastima on the other and Paul and angels on the other. Right, so
there's that that's he's the figure who opposes that that's why we talked about
one of the places we talked about Belial was in our
episode on the Antichrist. So if you want some more, you can go there. Because of that,
because the sort of the anti-Messiah, the anti-Christ, the opposition of Messiah is Boliol
in these texts. But just for some examples, Jubilee's 15, verse 32 is talking about the
uncircumcised Gentiles, they refer to as the sons of Boliol.
Yeah, which it doesn't mean literally, it just means that they do the works of their
quote unquote father.
Right. And why are they yolkless? Well, circumcision is here being used to refer to the Torah.
Yeah. Right. They're outside of the law. They don't have that yolk. And so they're like wild animals.
Right. It's the idea. Right. The testaments of the 12 patriarchs that we talked about a few
episodes ago refers to idolaters and sexually immoral people as sons of Boliol.
The extension of Isaiah, of course, in chapter
chapter 2 verse 4 that we talked about last time, this definitely personifies him.
It refers to the angel of lawlessness who is the ruler of this world, Boliol.
Right? So that's putting kind of a fighter point on it.
But this also shows up in St. Paul's epistles interestingly.
It's a second Corinthians 6 verse 15.
He says, what harmony is there between Christ and Boliol?
It's sort of an obvious statement, right?
Thank you.
like, how can you have harmony between Christ and the Antichrist?
Right?
That sort of...
Yeah, yeah.
Definitially impossible.
The Messiah and the like anti-Besiah.
Right.
But there is a much earlier mention, and that's in the book of Proverbs.
Right?
Book of Proverbs, yeah.
I was going to say, yeah, I mean, it's in Proverbs chapter 6.
Yeah.
Well, it's 12 through 15.
Yeah, it shows up in verse
12 but it goes on a little bit. So it says, well, if you read the E.S.V., I'll do that.
So it just kind of takes in here. A worthless person, a wicked man, goes about with crooked
speech, winks with his eyes, signals with his feet, points with his finger, with perverted
heart, devises evil, continually sowing discord. Therefore, calamity will come upon him suddenly
in a moment he will be broken beyond healing.
So this is one of these cases where
the translation kind of hides a little of what's going on.
That phrase that shows up at the beginning
into the ESV translates as a worthless person.
In Hebrew it says Adam Belial.
I'm sure I'm not saying it, but...
The Man of Belial.
But it's a Dom because instead of a noosh
because Adam right is at like,
it's like Anthropos, this is an archetype.
Humanity.
Right, so the man of Balaile is this is an archetype.
This is a type of person. This is a type of human. And then that type of human is described
in the rest of the quote.
But there are even more interesting translations.
Oh yes, okay.
I have to bring this up because, well number one, it's been a while since I did this.
I had someone ask me a reason like, how come you never play the jingle anymore?
It wasn't a decision. It just sort of didn't happen.
But yes.
Finally, today I threw you a bone.
Thank you so much.
Yeah. So the King James version of this verse, what the ESV translates as a worthless person,
but of course more literally says a man of Belial, the man of Belial.
The King James translates it as a naughty person.
naughty.
And, you know, for us living here in the
Decadent 21st century, that sounds pretty silly in naughty person.
Like, naughty is the word we used to refer to kids, maybe lawless kids.
But what's fun about this is, this isn't, this isn't early modern English translation
of this phrase.
They're translating it from the Hebrew.
and naughty might seem
crazy to us now. But actually, it's really a good translation. It wouldn't work now, but it was a really good translation back when it was done. Okay. So here's why. Well, naughty actually comes from ultimately it's it's from not an a UGHT, right, which we use as a kind of archaic way of saying nothing, like that will come to not meaning it will come to nothing.
But what's
fun is that not actually comes from Old English na'uight, which means no thing, so literally
it does mean nothing. But early on, Naughty was used to mean needy, meaning having nothing,
right, not possessing nothing, right? So there's nothing e, how you could might think of it.
but also that sense of not or nothing was all
used right around the same time in the late 14th century. So this is kind of a
late medieval period. Was used to mean something that's evil or immoral or
corrupt or unclean and it actually participates in the sense of not
spelled either an OUGHT or an AUGHT that sense of nothingness and it's it's
actually a very Boweithian idea that that the privation of good is what evil
is.
good is a thing and then, but evil is actually not a thing.
Nothing, right?
And so therefore, you also get the idea
that this means something that's insignificant
or meaningless or worthless.
It can also even be used for the number zero.
We still sometimes, like, I think British English
often uses not to mean zero.
So this early modern English translation of naughty
is actually really good in terms of translating
Man of Belial.
because it has this whole ball of nothingness, chaos, evil,
privation, worthlessness, lawlessness, all bound up in that.
So next time you call your kids naughty, just think about the gravity of what you're saying,
or at least what you would have been saying if you were living in the late 14th century.
So there we go. That was a good father and
Here we go, we get it before and after.
Well, we all learned something today.
We all, I hope we all did.
Don't want to be naughty.
Because that's just nothing.
The beguiling of naughtyness.
Yes, exactly.
Let's be resisted at all costs.
Exactly.
So, yeah, to sort of finish up this section, right?
As I mentioned, Belyles are sort of last named guy.
But there are also places where some of the figures we've talked about in some of our monster
episodes. Our annual help.
Halloween monster episodes. Also, sometimes get used to represent sort of the ultimate
evil. I'm like Leviathan or he met Leviathan especially for you, Hellraiser fans out there.
Yes earlier today, I did have to explain to Father Andrew what what Hellraiser is.
It's not just acupuncture gone really bad. I found out. I don't think he enjoyed or needed
to find that out but not at all.
Not me.
So I'll inform you of all kinds of things.
But yeah, so sometimes those figures
are used sort of portray the ultimate evil or chaos,
or to write in sort of an analogical way.
But so having now covered sort of these different sets
of patterns and names and figures
for the devil, qua, ultimate evil being,
or Arch Evil, Arch Devil.
When we get into our forthcoming third half here, we're going to talk about, what do we do with this?
How do we understand this?
Is this like a bunch of guys?
Is this like the council?
Is this like the Legion of Doom meeting a swamp somewhere, conspiring to destroy humanity?
Or like how should we consider what's going on with these different figures?
in the way scripture in particular, even more than the eternal.
and second-telejudice about the way Scripture in particular talks about them
and relates them to each other.
All right, we'll be right back with the third and final half of this episode of The Lord of Spirits.
Saint Paesio said,
Instead, every day you should try to plant in your soul something spiritual, which will
Jack something.
gently and sinful.
Replace the sinful images in your mind with holy words.
AtheniteUSA.com offers holy icons for those wishing to plant something spiritual in their
souls.
Immaculate 22-karat gold leaf and applied on solid wood.
A lifelong gift for yourself and someone you care for.
Use the code Faith for free shipping.
Come and see atteniteUSA.com.
And we're back. It's the third and final half of this episode of the Lord of Spirits
are talking about the devils. And we just kind of did a catalog of a number of these
major devil figures that are found in Scripture and also Second Temple Jewish literature and elsewhere.
So now we're going to try to bring it all together, understand exactly what's going on.
the wave you've seen devils.
It makes it sound like you're spelling it with a Z.
You know, spelling is...
Which is very 90s?
Right.
I mean, in some level we are children of the 90s,
and of the 80s I guess, more of the 80s I think to the 90s.
Yeah.
But that's just what I visualized.
Spray painted by the way.
Devils with a Z, you know.
and maybe two Vs or a Y in there somewhere.
Now you just, the Z does it.
The Z's enough.
Yeah, the Z makes it copyrightable.
It makes it happen cool.
Why is there a Z in Dragon Ball Z?
I've never watched that show.
I don't understand what that's about.
That's past my time too.
The 9000 thing.
Yeah, I know the memes.
But I know that's all I know.
I don't know.
Okay.
Well.
Okay, no, can't help you out on that one.
Okay.
So what about the fact that close to?
Yeah, the gaping hole in my pop culture knowledge that will remain forever is anime.
Ha!
I'm about to lose a ton of our listeners, but I have just
anime, boars me. Wow.
Like I've seen the like really classic stuff. Yeah, like because like I tried I tried way back in the long ago time
Like late 80s, early 90s, I tried to get into it, right? So like
I've seen Akira, I've seen Ghost of the Shell, I've seen Apple Seed, I've seen Project Ako, I've seen Ninja Scroll, I've seen all this stuff, like, it's never done it for me.
Princess Modern, okay.
Yeah, it's hot, no, Totoro, yeah, I've seen that very early, like older stuff.
Did you know that the people who made, who were the rank and
bass, rank and bass animators who made like you know the hobbit.
original Hobbit movie. I shouldn't say the original Hobbit movie because there's one of
the 60s that was called Hobbit exclamation point. You can see that on YouTube. But yeah,
the Hobbit movie that most people think about, and then they made the return of the King
same style. They went on to form the group that I can't remember the name of it now,
that made Princess Mononoke and so forth. So it was kind of like a pre-anime thing.
Yeah. Yeah. So like I've seen it, it just...
I just didn't work for you.
Yeah, I could tell you everything of the world about European and American comics, but
I know nothing about manga.
Like, huh.
Yeah.
I probably know less than you about it, but I also don't claim to have everything about
pop culture.
With manga, right?
You saw Giojimbo, right, like Lone Wolf and Cub, like the old stuff, Blade of the Immortal,
like I tried.
Yeah.
you
Yeah, just not my thing.
All right.
So what do we do with the fact that there are multiple references
to the evil one, and yet we have all these various spirits?
Well, yeah.
And we went through, when we were going through those,
we kind of went through the places where
the name was used in Scripture or where
it's associated directly with a story in Scripture.
But like in the New Testament, there's
bunch of rap.
It's clearly referring to a devil figure, but it's not totally clear which one.
Right? So they're just kind of ambiguous references.
So some of these just refer to the evil one. Right? The evil one. Well which one evil one? Right?
So one of the most famous ones is potentially in the Lord's Prayer.
Yes.
And I am going to have to grind an ax here for a minute.
All right.
Just briefly.
And this is, listen guys, for those of you who think I'm always picking on our Protestant
friends or our Roman Catholic friends, this is mostly an issue I have with my fellow Orthodox
folks, right?
So in Orthodox translations of the Lord's Prayer, some of them end with delivers for
evil, some with delivers from the evil one.
Right?
And every once in a while,
some Orthodox person who knows some Greek,
sometimes I think the problem is that they know more modern Greek than
actually Greek here.
We'll say, oh, well, in the original Greek, it's the evil one.
And sometimes they'll even like post the original Greek to say see resolved.
A book to 20 is two options. Yes. Yes. Right. And I think they think that because there's an article in front of Ponyru, that that makes it the evil one.
But therefore the adjective evil is being
used substantively, right? And that could mean the evil man, the evil person, the evil one.
It's not that that's an impossible translation. It could mean that. Yeah. But here's the problem.
Greek also puts an article before an adjectival quality to talk about that quality itself.
So...
For example, famously, this is sometimes reflected in English translations.
They'll have Plato or Aristotle talking about the good, which is an over translation.
Right? They're talking about good or goodness itself.
You use the article to do that. It's called the monadic article.
Right? You use the article to do that. And so in Greek, the reason we have
Please
different translations is that Oopone Roo could be the evil one or it could be just evil,
like evil itself. Yeah, deliver us from evil. The Greek is ambiguous. So stop posting the Greek
as if that solves the issue, right? You may think you're pulling rank because you know some
some Greek on people, but really, you're exposed.
yourself as someone who doesn't.
Which is split it down the middle and say deliver us from the evil.
From the evil. Yeah.
Everybody just be like, what?
But anyway, both are fine.
That acts ground to do whatever is normal in your parish.
Right. Assuming that's the evil one, right?
Which it could be.
Yeah.
It could be deliberately ambiguous.
Remember what we were talking about back in the first half, right?
Maybe it's happy.
you as on purpose. But if we're going to interpret that as being referring to the evil one,
devil, Satan, the zeal, the liel, right?
Masterma even. Which one? Not clear. The, and Christ gives the parable of the sower.
And the parable of the saw, there's the seed that falls in different places.
the seed that falls on the road, the birds come in and eat it before it can take root.
And when he gives the interpretation to his disciples, he says, the birds plural are the evil one.
Who comes and snatches away? Well, which one? I mean, even if you go with bird imagery,
as we talked about in Jubilee's,
uh, master was represented as a crow.
But Azazel has the Raven stuff going on.
Yeah.
Is it one of them?
Could be, but it doesn't say.
Right?
In Ephesians 6, 16, St. Paul talks about the flaming darts of the evil one.
Flaming darts are owned by the evil one.
Well, that doesn't sound like any of the people we talked about so far tonight.
That's
We've talked about another context, including the forehorses of the apocalypse,
Refesh, right, with his archery, the Flanieros, right?
That's what the Flanieros are.
Which you see, like, with Apollo and the Iliad.
He shoots a bunch of arrows of people and they get diseases.
I'm glad you saw that I wasn't making that up, by the way.
We read the Elyt recently.
Yes, we gave examples when we were talking about his asal of those quotes from
first John where it sounded like St. John was using a asal language but he'd
never used the name as asal. He referred to the devil, he referred to the evil
one, the wicked one. Say, Paul of the...
We had a second Thessalonians praise that they would be protected from the evil one.
Which one?
Well, second Thessalonians is where he talks about the man of lawlessness.
Is he talking about the Lyle?
Maybe.
John 17 verse 15.
During Christ what's called his high priestly prayer, he praise that the Father would protect
his followers from the evil one.
There is no clue as to which one, which version, or you want to see it, that would be talking about.
Then, beyond the evil one language, you have three times in St. John's Gospel, in 12 verse 31, 14 verse 30, and 16 verse 11, Christ refers to the ruler of this world,
Right, as this entity that's sort of coming for him with the
crucifixion. Right, that's coming after him. Which one's that? Right? At one point he says that
the rule of this world found nothing in him. Right? Had no claim on him. So is that like Satan?
Like there's no accusation he can make against Christ because he's sinless. Or right, you could say it's
It's a zazel outside the camp kind of.
ruling the world idea since he's coming after Jesus the Messiah is this like
Boliol like the anti-Musah right like not clear right and the same things
true when St. Paul and 2 Corinthians 4 verse 4 refers to the God of this age
right or St. Paul I 1st
Corinthians 2 verse 8.
refers to the rulers of this world, rulers plural.
In a way that's clearly referring to powers and
principalities, right?
Like, demonic spirits.
So it's not clear who in terms of these names and these
identities we've been talking about they're referring to.
But we have to back up then and even ask a kind of different
question that precedes that which is
In any of those examples I just ran through, or any of those speakers or writers, Christ,
St. Paul, whoever we're talking about, St. John, are they even meaning to refer to one
of these to the exclusion of the others?
Do they even necessarily have in mind, oh, I'm talking about a zeal, not the devil, right?
Where I'm talking about Satan not man.
asthma. Yeah, I mean, it kind of raises this question of like,
could this could these all be different names and sets of imagery
referring to one particular figure or a set of figures that is
smaller than the than the total number. You know, one or two.
Yeah, exactly, could this could the Satan in the devil be two
of one guy and then a Zazel and mastermer.
like, you know, right, right?
Right.
Are these names and these patterns not describing the identity of a being, but describing like,
like actions like the works right in the world.
Yeah.
And if that's the case, then could you have one entity who acts in these different ways
and the different names and stuff are ways of talking about those different actions?
Yeah.
but there even be.
like could the set of the the beings who are doing these things actually be a larger
number than the list of names that we just gave like yeah which we've talked I mean we've
presented that idea before like like when Norse Pagan's worship Thor is there just one demon or
is there maybe a set of demons that are all saying I'm Thor and accepting that worship from them
Right.
There are certainly more than five, six demons.
They're out there.
However you count them, there's definitely a lot.
I mean, Legion was possessed by more than five-six.
So we don't think all of them were possessed, Legion.
Because then there wouldn't be any left after they went into the pigs.
Good point.
Right.
And so there's that question.
But now we even have to back up another step.
Right?
Let's go.
we have to back up is because we're talking about, we're trying to identify an evil spirit
or spirits, right? Like which one? Like to identify, name it, describe it, right? But how
does identity even work for spirits, evil or otherwise?
Right. I mean, for humans, identity is very much bound up in body, frankly. You know,
We'll be talking more about that soon.
Yes, as I cut.
to the bodily resurrection and stuff.
Not this episode.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah.
In the near future of future episodes, right?
But like, so how does that even work?
So there is a sense of identity for Spirits
because we've got, right?
We could look at not on the demonic side
but like the Archangel Gabriel, the Archangel Michael,
the Archangel Raphael, right?
Who are named?
Right?
The Archangel Gabriel appears at multiple points in scripture
and gives his name as an identifier
in a case that he's the same spirit.
that appeared in those other places, right?
And did things in those other places.
So there is a sense of identity.
And remember, as we've talked about on the show,
per, say, John DeMaskis and others,
angelic beings and therefore,
demonic beings are not truly bodyless.
Yeah, they have sort of ephemeral bodies.
They have...
spirit bodies. I mean St. John Damascus tackles this question by leaving it ambiguous.
He essentially says he puts it comparatively. He says it basically compared to us,
their bodyless, but compared to God, they are definitely circumscribed.
They have a body. And mastima and his ilk, right, that we want to take that,
literally, they had human bodies and will again in the resurrection when they're judged.
So there's a body associated with them, right?
In that case, too.
But if we look at the ones that are angelic beings who, quote unquote,
fell in various ways, they have some kind of a femoral body,
does that then translate to them having an ephemeral identity?
Right.
In the same way that their body experiences less finitude,
They're still fine.
because they're created, but less finitude than a human body.
Does their less finitude to their identity?
This is a question I'm not going to answer here.
Yeah, I mean, I hope you're not hoping for me to resolve this problem.
Yeah, we're the point of all this problematizing
to use good postmodern philosophical length.
which is to point out that that's not what actually really matters.
Right. And Jellic and demonic beings, we talk about them as these discrete beings.
We talk about them basically as invisible humans with wings.
Let's be honest, either bat wings or bird wings.
Which, which I mean, this is how they get depicted in art because like,
how old would you draw them, you know, right?
But it's interesting even in iconography.
which tends to depict, like there's about three or four different colors that they usually get used.
So like there's black, black, not black as in human black, but black, black, truly black.
And then white, truly white. You can see truly, truly white. Like it's Serbian iconography
often. They depict it as very, very white. I've seen green, I've seen brown. Those are less common.
But they're almost always depicted as very sort of two-dimensional. Like there's no
no substance.
them. And they're often smaller than humans too. Yeah. So like this, it's an attempt with
art to depict something that does not manifest in the 3D world in the way that you and I manifest
in the 3D world and could be put on a bathroom scale and, you know, eat dinner, right?
It's, so that's art, but we shouldn't, we shouldn't materialize the art. You know, it's materializing
it enough right yeah
Yeah. Yeah. Because I mean, if you want to
literalize it, then you say, well, Father,
Steven, you said earlier, the sitting sorry and said,
St. Michael is a is a, a, a,
Sarah, and why isn't he depicted as a snake?
Right.
Or the other ways that Sarah certainly depicted, right?
Right. That's an over literalization. Right.
That triggers that question, right?
Cause he doesn't have a physical, physical form. Right.
What he appears he appears here?
in some form, right? But that's an appearance, right, that he is giving, right? And so if
we understand that the way we talk about identity, because again, we only have human experiences,
you have never had an experience other than a human experience, right? You've never had
a bat experience, we've also never had an angel experience, right?
So we have to talk about things in human terms.
We have to, right?
That's why God speaks to us that way in the scriptures.
So we got it.
Because that's all we can understand, right?
So it's natural for us to kind of do that.
But we have to have this kind of problematization
to realize that even when we're talking about things
other than humans, it doesn't necessarily reflect reality.
Accurately.
Yeah, it's an attempt to reach towards it
to do the best that we can.
Yeah. And so that means that, right? That means that if we understand that our concept of
identity applies only in a kind of a femoral shifting way to demonic beings, right? Further
that there are beings of chaos and deception, etc. etc. Right.
But that they, right, that it applies to them only in this ephemeral shifting kind of way, right?
That's exactly how the scriptures talk about them.
That fits with references to the evil one that kind of play into one of those
conceptions, but not but kind of ambiguously.
Right.
At this represents a difference, you may notice.
between the kind of confident way in which Second Temple Jewish literature even talks about these figures, like outside the Scriptures, talks about these figures.
They're very quick to say, oh yeah, as aesol, serpent in the garden, that was a zeal, that was a zeal, a zeal's like this. Here's what a zeal looks like.
A zeal is a zeal is a zeal, right? Here's how he's going to be to send a temple literature. Whereas the Scriptures,
It's the goat spirit of the wilderness, right?
It's much...
bigger and more ephemeral, right? And then human interpreters just had to describe it again in a more human way that more literalizes it and more makes him sort of an evil human with superpowers. He's basically a supervillain.
Right.
If you take those second double Jewish literature descriptions literally, right?
He's like brainiac or bizarro or something.
Right.
Like.
Well, he's a born of a smooth talker than Pizarro.
Yeah.
And so that being the case, that means that us trying to nail it down.
Right. Which version of the devil is this author in the New Testament or this church father even trying to talk about here in this place?
That's kind of a waste of time.
Yeah.
That's not how and why they talk about the evil one or the devil or Satan or whichever title they're using
They're referring to this evil spirit
the sort of principle evil spirit
Right that that that dominates the world and
So we're not gonna obviously we're not gonna repeat our whole
what is a spirit episode, right?
What is a spirit when it's in home?
go listen to that. But to touch on that, right, what are we talking about when we're talking about an
evil spirit is we're talking about a kind of collective consciousness, right? Meaning a consciousness
that includes other conscious beings within it, which has agency.
And that agency takes the form of being able to move
those subsidiary consciousnesses.
Right. So what does that mean? Right. Without it. I don't want to go back and listen to that three hour episode.
What does that mean for other steve? Okay. So that's.
So we'll start with something very clear like the synoptic gospels and acts. Right. Demon possession.
Yeah, where a demon grabs hold or demons grab hold
a person and control their body and sometimes even talk through that person.
Right.
And so it possesses them.
We, we, we're so familiar with that language, right?
This person is possessed by a demon.
Meaning the demon like owns them.
Yeah.
Like has them in its clutches, has them in its grasp, right, is controlling them.
That person is still conscious.
That person is not unconscious all the time.
you
They couldn't ask for help, right?
Or they wouldn't have people around the masking for help
if they were, right?
And we hear it described in that way
in the synoptic hospitals, right?
The father who says,
a demon ceases my son and does this, right?
Like that means his son was not constantly
like only speaking as and acting as the demon, right?
That consciousness is still there,
but there is this sort of...
overlapping demonic consciousness that's sort of in the driver's seat, that's
moving it, that's pushing and pulling and twisting and seducing and filtering
and right and so if we start with that we can see that phenomenon in
scripture right now we take that and we broaden that out to a collective to a
group of people. They can be any size group from a fan
family to a nation, right, to the world, frankly.
Yeah.
Right, ruler of this world.
Right.
And we could see examples, right, as long time listeners know, I'm getting tired of
always using mid-twentieth century Germans as the example of bad people.
So...
The Camer Rouge, right?
Look, it's either 19th century German scholars or mid-20th century Germans.
Right.
So I'm assuring both of those.
A big more creative than that.
There you go.
The Camer Rouge, right?
You have a group that is being moved by a spirit to do things that
Quarer quote individuals, like a person who's a member of that group.
If you had talked to them before or you talked to them after, it's horrified by.
And wouldn't necessarily choose to do themselves because they find it horrifying.
When they're functioning within that group, they're driven by something.
Because something that's more than just the sum of the individual people there.
That drives them towards actions.
You can see this in...
sort of out breaks. Even the Khmer Rouge was for a limited time mid-20th century
German fascism was for a limited time the Bolsheviks were for a limited time right whoever we want to pick right
cultural revolution in China
Whatever example we want to pick at any point. I think frankly a lot of what happened in the Crusades
Like you look at the
when they got the sack of Jerusalem or the sack of Constantinople in the fourth crusade.
Right riots we have these individual outbreaks of things where we can kind of see okay
Yeah, I see that these people they get in this riot they do these or they're they're ashamed of afterwards
They were grit afterwards and that if you'd said to them, hey, why don't you go do this? They would be like no
I would never do that right, but this can also be longer term and become entrenched
Right in societies and cultures. Yeah, it can be come to you cultural tradition, you know
Yes keep doing culture tradition
institutionalized in law.
I mean, or even patterns within families.
Yeah.
Like, we've all known families where there's something about them.
And sometimes it's multi-generational.
Yeah.
But you look at, you look at like the Roman Empire, right?
Petrasty was an institution.
In the Roman Empire.
Yeah.
Right.
You look at the way they treated, not just the Jewish people,
but any of the sort of
natives of conquered lands who didn't have Roman citizenship.
That was institutionalized.
Slavery was institutionalized.
So it wasn't just that there was some spirit in their motivating people to do
something, but they were so captured by it that those things just seem normal to
them.
They didn't even think about them.
This is whether they were bad or good, right? Like they just were. Yeah.
They were just facts.
Aristotle could look at slavery and be like, no, this is just natural.
This is the way things are. Right?
So this can be and it's not always this sort of gross and violent and obvious as like a riot breaking out.
It could be very subtle.
It can go on from...
centuries. It can be deeply entrenched. As we've said before,
demonic powers are more than willing to play the long game. They live a lot longer than humans.
Right. And to corrupt and to push and to pull. And trust me, there are a bunch of them behind.
Right. I'm an America behind United States culture going on right now. You probably don't
have to think hard to name them. The ones that are really dangerous, though, are the ones that you
You can't name.
Because like Petter asked your slavery in the Roman Empire, they've been institutionalized
so much that you don't even think anything of them.
But they're just the way things are.
The ones we'd rattle off, not that those aren't bad.
Obviously the portification of American culture is horrible.
That is a spirit behind that.
off-licacy, violence, right?
There's all kinds of things we could talk about
American culture that are obvious to us as Christians,
but there are a whole bunch built to do
American culture.
Then again, we don't even think about.
We don't even think about,
because they're just normal.
They're just the way the things are.
And that's sort of the ultimate long game
demonic delusion.
And so when the scriptures and the fathers
talk about
these spirits. It's not primarily to try to tell us something about the particulars of
a spiritual being. I'd be able to identify him. Right. Well, who was the server of the
guard? Was that the devil? Was that Satan? Was that a zeal? Right. Scriptures never
talk about anything for this reason, frankly. But this either, right, it's to help us identify
those spirits to help us discern those
spirits to see where they're acting and acting toward our destruction. Right? Because once we've
uncovered that, we've discerned what spirit is behind something. That's when we can fight against it.
Yeah. So let's let's re-approach here at the close of of this episode. Let's re-approach
The devils that we've talked about in this episode from from this perspective.
from the perspective that these are spirits that you need to discern at work in the world.
So what do we have with the devil? The way we talked about him in the first half.
Yeah, I mean rebellion and envy. Right. His envy of humanity. Right. And his rebellion against God.
Scott. Yeah, here he bells basically because of his envy. As it says, you know, the
fell through envy. Right. It's the where you see envy, whether you see it in your own soul,
whether you see it in your community, whether you see it in culture at large, wherever you see rebellion.
Right. You should discern. Right. This is the spirit of the devil at work. Right.
Look at the Satan, the way we talked about him. Yeah, the accuser. Right. What does he about?
Slander condemning others.
Right?
Finding fault.
Yeah.
Rather than working toward someone's good.
It's interesting how often these two sets go together.
Like someone whose envy is of someone else might then slander them.
For instance.
Yes.
Yeah.
That's why there aren't fights between demons.
Right.
Not really.
Like they're...
They're all after the same thing.
the same thing.
It is depicted that way in pagan literature, but that's not what's like like the Iliad, right?
You know, you got some Greek gods against some Greek gods, but really the whole point of it is,
and you can see this in the text, that it's to get these humans to fight with each other,
but the gods are all kind of ultimately okay with each other in the end.
Yeah, sometimes they slip sides back and forth.
Yeah, yeah.
The idea is to get the people to fight going.
Yeah, arm both sides.
You know, yeah, let them destroy each other
Or look at his nasal right what's his nasal about seduction and sexual immorality
Right a desire for knowledge at the expense of morality secret knowledge as otarica
Yeah, and corruption
Right
again
Look at
Arcontemporary culture
Look at what science is doing.
Look at sexual immorality, right, right, right, right, right, right, like these are spirits at work. Right. We need to be able to identify them and resist them.
Right.
What's masterma all about?
Well, masterma doesn't have a body.
Right?
He's a parasite.
Right? Paracidism.
Right? He's about...
leaching off of what is, right?
Not, well, because he can't, but not creating something, right?
Not building anything, those things that God created humanity to do, put things in order
to fill them with life.
No, leach off of them, break them down.
Right?
Belial, obviously, lawlessness.
Yeah.
of discipline, lack of self control, lack of
control. Go to the monsters, right? Leviathan and Behemoth. On one side, you've got chaos and destruction.
Right? On the other side, you've got tyranny. Right? Order at the expense of life.
Right? We've got to be able to discern that. Again, first of all, within ourselves,
right in our families and our communities.
and fight against it. That's the point of talking about identifying the evil one.
To help us find him when he's at work. Not to give us some esoteric information about his identity.
Yes, I feel like we get back to this theme a lot.
You know, like the show is not about weird spiritual esoterica.
Although, you know, I don't blame someone who that's what they came for.
Right.
If you hear for that listener, welcome.
But God willing, we have executed a good bait and switch here.
Not that we ever lied to you.
It's really that we were pretty upfront about what it is we're doing.
So for my final thoughts about this episode about the devils, I thought I would read from
Ephesians chapter 6 because I think this is super relevant.
So I'm going to start with verse 10 and go through verse 20.
See Paul's
says, finally, be strong in the Lord and in the strength of his might.
Put on the whole armor of God that you may be able to stand against the schemes of the
devil.
For we do not wrestle against flesh and blood, but against the rulers, against the authorities,
against the cosmic powers over this present darkness, against the spiritual forces of
evil in the heavenly places.
Therefore take up the whole armor of God that you may be able to withstand in the evil
day and having done all to stand firm. Stand therefor.
having fastened on the belt of truth,
and having put on the breastplate of righteousness.
And as shoes for your feet,
having put on the readiness given by the gospel of peace,
in all circumstances, take up the shield of faith
with which you can extinguish all the flaming darts
of the evil one, and take the helmet of salvation
and the sword of the Spirit, which is the word of God,
praying at all times in the Spirit
with all prayer and supplication.
To that end, keep alert with all perseverance,
making supplication for all the same.
And also for me, that words may be given to me in opening my mouth boldly to proclaim the mystery of the Gospel,
for which I am an ambassador in chains that I may declare it boldly as I ought to speak.
I picked this not just because, I mean if you listen to this obviously there's a bunch of references to things that we just talked about.
Not only is there the devil, but also these various demonic forces he talks about.
even references the flaming darts of the evil one,
that's the the refish,
Roshif, I can never remember which way it goes.
Anyways, the dart throwing guy with the plagues and stuff.
But what to me is really important about this
is he's giving practical instruction here
to the Ephesians.
He's, again, he's not just giving a kind of demonology.
Like here's a big list of demons, you know, and how can you identify them?
Whatever the point is to be in the fight to be ready for battle
right and
First of all this underlines the true nature of spiritual warfare as he says
We do not wrestle against flesh and blood but against the rulers authorities this present darkness spiritual forces of evil in the heavenly places
I don't think we can underline that point enough
Because number one, the world is pretty crazy right now.
Now, I've been alive long enough to know, to recognize that the world has always been
crazy.
Now, I'm not going to claim it doesn't get better and worse.
It definitely gets better and worse.
And maybe we're on a worse swing right now.
I don't know.
I do know that for a lot of people, it feels that way.
Right?
And when it feels that way, that means we're going to act that way.
going to respond that way. One of the ways that people are responding to this sense that
the world is getting nuttier and nuttier, that we live in clown world, right? That there's
more and more darkness. One of the ways that people respond is by attempting to expose it
as though the exposing of it.
is what it means to fight this battle. Right? Now, I'm not saying that evil encryption
should not be exposed. I'm not saying that. I'm not saying that at all. Right?
If there is a way to bring justice, it should be brought. But the simple fact of
of protest, right, of make...
Expose a kind of religion to itself, right? This often I think appeals to
frankly the spirit of Azazel. It's a desire for secret knowledge. Look, I know
what's really going on in the world. I have it. I have the knowledge that no one
C's you know wake up sheep all this is
very common now. It's very, very common. Curseing the darkness, frankly. But what you don't see
say Paul saying here is that that's the way to go. Again, I'm not saying that evil should not
be exposed and dealt with, you know, if you can do something about evil, you should do that thing.
If you can do something about it, like if you can make something right that has been made wrong.
But what he does focus on here is what it means for each of us to actually...
fight against the darkness. This present darkness, as he uses the phrase. And of course, that was a very
famous, well, Frank Peretti was mentioned already. That was the name of his big, big best-selling book.
He says, to put on the whole armor of God, he talks about the belt of truth, the breastplate of
righteousness, the shoes that are about the readiness of the gospel of peace, the shield of faith,
the helmet of salvation, the sword...
of the Spirit which is the Word of God, praying at all times in the Spirit he says with prayer
and supplication, keeping alert with perseverance, praying for the saints.
This is about the things that you do. This is about your actual personal spiritual life,
which anybody can complain about bad things going on in the world. I mean, and you can make a lot
of money doing it frankly. There are whole industries based on this.
But what it means to actually engage in spiritual warfare is fighting against the demons by living in this faithful way.
Right? Living for truth, living in a righteous way, preaching the gospel, becoming more faithful.
Knowing the scriptures, knowing the Lord Jesus Christ better and better, being serious about prayer for other people.
I don't know.
These are the things that actually are the front line of the spiritual battle.
It's very tempting to feel like getting out into the public conversation about whatever is
the hot thing right now is that to feel like that's the front line. Like, look at me, I'm out there,
I'm a big warrior. But if you're not doing anything in your heart, if you're not actually increasing
your faithfulness if you're not actually loving your neighbor right if you're
not actually helping the people next to you and you get out on that line. I'm sorry,
but you get shot in the first five minutes. You're not actually fighting against the enemy.
You're getting massacred by the enemy because you're walking out there without the whole
You're getting wasted.
You know, destroyed.
The demons, your...
easy picking. You're easy picking. So that's why St. Paul says this is to really, really
become serious about the Christian life. And it's not just something you do in your
closet. It's about active love for your family, for your neighbor, for your fellow parishioners,
right? This is about the 3D stuff. Anybody can be a complainer. And maybe this is the
you
someone's really good at complaining.
Maybe they're really good at finding out all the bad things
that governments and whoever else are doing.
I mean, you know, news flash,
governments are doing bad things.
Doesn't mean it's okay,
but it has been kind of going on as long as humans
have had history.
We see that in the scripture,
we see that throughout history.
But the point of talking about devils,
the point of talking about evil spirits
is not so that we
gain some esoteric knowledge. This is not esoteric knowledge actually. This is most of it, simply written
there in scripture, so it's just a matter of reading what's there. It is the most available book in
the world. Okay, it's not a secret. You know, this is not something that only the really
the illumined know about. This is public. This is available for all. And where it actually
hits the road is in the
daily struggle to live as Christians, the daily struggle to live as Christians. So if you
really want to make a difference in the world, follow what St. Paul says here in Ephesians
chapter 6. If you really want to do battle against the enemy and you really want to give a beat
down to the demons, love your neighbor, including your neighbor who doesn't says things that are bad.
including them, especially them. After all, the Lord Jesus said, love your enemies.
And by that he means other humans. That wasn't an option. He didn't say, you know,
if you're super duper saint, you can love your enemies. He says, love your enemies,
bless those who curse you, do good to those who hurt you.
This is the...
of Christ. And the real spiritual battle is fought by putting on the whole
armor of God and taking up these weapons. We don't fight as the world fights.
As the Lord says, my kingdom is not of this world. And so we need to take on the
tools, the weapons, the armor that are not of this world and stop wasting our
times with the ones that are of this world. It's waste and it can even
be harmful to us and to other people. That's what I have to say about that.
So to kind of continue the metaphor, as it's something similar to this way back in the long ago
time, I think my memories are vague and I don't go back and listen to the show. But
But one of the real dangers of not-
understanding spiritual warfare like what Andrew was just talking about, or even denying that the
spiritual world is real is that it's sort of like trying to walk through a battlefield wearing a
blindfold. Right? No wonder how much you refuse to see it or acknowledge it or try to believe it
doesn't exist. It's still a battlefield and you're not going to last long. And so I think this idea
that we talked about here at the end of the...
episode of discernment, discerning the spirits, which is actually all through the New Testament.
Testing the spirits.
Here's an important one that we've, I think, mostly lost sight of in
modern world. And as I said during that section, this really needs to start with
ourselves. This is echoing some of what Father Andrew just said.
We're very good at actually, well, I should say very good.
We're better.
at identifying these things out in society, out in culture.
The farther they are from us,
the farther it is from me,
the better I am at identifying it.
But when it comes to inside myself,
that's where things get hazy.
And the reason I say we've gotten really bad about at it,
and forgotten it is,
Let me talk to all my fellow people.
who identify as Christians here, stop blaming the Holy Spirit for your garbage.
It's blasphemy.
When you say, I was led by the Holy Spirit to do blank, and you're wrong, which you usually are,
it was usually your idea and your decision, you are committing an act of blasphemy.
against the Holy Spirit. You can look up how serious that is.
Right. If you preach, stop saying while I was good to talk about something else, but
the Holy Spirit led me to say this, because I can't count the number of times I've heard
someone say that, and then for example make a basic factual error about the Greek that
they're talking about. Which means guess what Charlie? The Holy Spirit didn't tell you
that error.
You changed your mind about what you want to talk about.
That wasn't the Holy Spirit.
Okay.
Not only we lost the idea of discerning the spirits,
we now just stamp our own decisions and our own ideas
with the Holy Spirit, maybe because I don't know we were praying
about something when it occurred to us,
or just as a way of speaking.
Right.
Well, experience is God.
Stop blaming God for your garbage.
What discerning the Spirit's means is, when I talk about inside myself, so we've talked
about before on the show, my thoughts don't come from me.
I don't generate them.
They come into my head from outside, just like sights or sounds or smells.
And then I have to discern them.
I have to examine them, my thoughts, my attitudes, my ideas, my motivations, and say, what spirit
is this movement within me coming from?
Is it coming from the Holy Spirit or is it coming from some other spirit, including
my spirit?
My spirit is not the Holy Spirit, and I need to follow the Holy Spirit not mine.
Because mine is too subject to influence from those other ones.
And mine is sinful in a variety of ways.
Rather than analyzing our actions, we try to stamp them with the divine authority.
Because we're not even used to thinking this way.
We're not even used to taking a step back.
a good place
start to be practical. A good place to start with this is at the end of the day. I think this is
one of the reasons why Christians have always had evening prayers. Well, frankly, God's people
have had evening prayers going back to the Tabernacle, going back to Exodus, going back to the Torah.
Because that's a point at which you can take stock of the day. You can look at the things you did,
the things you thought. The places where you paused in thought and dwelt on certain thoughts.
ideas. The things you didn't do, the things you avoided doing, the responsibilities
you didn't live up to. And you could start to sift through them. Start to sift
through them and say, where are the things where God blessed me? Maybe God came in
and stopped me from doing something I shouldn't. And that was the movement, right?
That was...
the push. It was a push in the right direction away from something bad. We're
pushing the right direction to do something good. Those it's okay to give credit
to God. Those you should give credit to God. And then where are the places where I
was doing my own will, or maybe where I've even been shoved by something else?
In the wrong direction or away from the right direction. Then once you've
gotten you
to doing that at the end of the day retrospectively, looking back at things. The more you do it,
the better you'll get at it. And then you'll start being able to do it a little better in the moment
when the idea pops into your head before you act on it, before you speak. You pause and think,
Where did that just come from?
Why is that here?
Is that something I want to keep around or something I need to toss out?
And the more you do that, the better you get at that.
And then you can start doing it aimed toward the future.
Then you really start to recognize the spirit of God.
What he's acting in you, what he's acting in your family and your community and the world.
You can start to recognize them and you can start acting to try and get on board.
Here's where I see the spirit moving in some direction.
I'm going to follow.
Here's where I see some other spirit moving, including my own.
I need to resist that.
I need to push back on that. I need to get away from that.
You can't do any of this non-deliberately.
None of this will start happening by accident.
This only happens when we make a conscious
effort to pursue it, to work on it, to get better at it.
Trying to sift and sort out these things.
And we can do what St. Paul says, we can cling to what is good.
We can flee from what is evil.
Maybe it's because we've been taught for so long that you're not
supposed to judge.
We're not supposed to make, you know,
Here's the
difference between discriminating against people and discriminating between good and evil.
There's a difference between judgment and discernment.
Maybe it's because we've been taught so long we're not supposed to do those things
that we don't bother.
But we're being led into destruction.
We're blaming God for things and failing to give him credit for things.
along the way. So this should be a call, again, not to try to construct a cool
demonology, not to get cool AI sketches of the different levels we talked about.
But to actually start pursuing what we're called to, and what all of these
references in the scriptures and outside are really calling us to, start learning
How to discern.
Start learning how to see
Spiritually what's going on in SN around us and through some discipline effort
Get good at
Clinging to what is good and fleeing from a zeal
Amen well that wraps up our episode on the doubles. Thank you very much for listening everyone
We'd like to hear from you. You can hear us at Lord of Spirit today.
You can message us on Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com slash
word of spirits.
God willing, we'll be back live for our first July episodes,
so that'll be coming up.
If you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity
or you need help to find a parish,
we highly recommend going to Orthodoxintro.org.
Enjoy this for our live broadcast on the second and fourth
Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern,
4 p.m. Pacific.
I watch with...
Glee while your Kings and Queens
went for 10 decades with the gods they made.
If you are on Facebook, which probably Steven is not,
you can follow our page.
You can also join our discussion group.
Leave ratings and reviews wherever you get your podcasts
and please share this show with a friend
who's going to benefit from it.
I'd probably be sure to go to achiefaith.com,
stroke support and help make sure we
had lots of other AFR podcasts or stay on the air.
And I lay traps for troubadours.
get killed before they reach
Bombay. Thank you. Good night. God bless.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio. And I be held, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne
and the beasts and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands
of thousands. Same with a loud voice.
worthy is the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom and
strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.